<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parents groans over their wicked children several sermons on Prov. XVII, 25, published for the benefit of all, but especially of good parents and their children / by Edward Lawrence ...</title>
            <author>Lawrence, Edward, 1623-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13208088</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13208088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 425:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Parents groans over their wicked children several sermons on Prov. XVII, 25, published for the benefit of all, but especially of good parents and their children / by Edward Lawrence ...</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, Edward, 1623-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ... and Joseph Collier ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in National Library of Scotland (Advocates').</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XVII, 25 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Parent and child --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Children --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Children --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Parents Groans</hi> OVER THEIR Wicked Children. SEVERAL SERMONS On <hi>PROV.</hi> XVII. 25. Publiſhed for the Benefit of all, but eſpecially of good Parents and their Children.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD LAWRENCE,</hi> M. A. ſometimes Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church,</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 2.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>—Notwithſtanding they hearkened not unto the voice of their Father, becauſe the Lord would ſlay them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel:</hi> and <hi>Joſeph Collier</hi> at the <hi>Bible,</hi> under the Gate, on <hi>London-Bridge.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:2"/>
            <head>To my beloved Children, <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Samuel, Edward, John, Thomas, Elizabeth, Mary, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin, Nathanael;</hi> and to all the Children of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Children!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am ſenſible of my unworthineſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſs to be ſeen in Print; it is now above Twenty years ſince, by the power and goodneſs of God, I was unexpectedly reſcued from the jaws of death, which was the reaſon I then publiſhed that little book, called, <hi>Chriſts Power over bodily Diſeaſes:</hi> and I had never been the Author of a book of this Title, had not two of you, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially one made me the Father of fools.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here ſay no more particularly to you two, but that ſound repentance, and the fruits thereof, in a ſetled reformation of life, will yet be your glory, and my joy; but if ye hate to be reform'd, (which God forbid) I ſhall mourn till I dye for the loſs of Children, but ye will be tormented for ever for the loſs of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Children!</hi> I have not of the things of this world to leave you. I do acknowledge the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb facs="tcp:98500:3"/>of God in not judging me ſit to be intruſted with theſe things; but it's enough for us if we can call God our own, though we cannot call the riches of the world our own; ſome of you do with comfort remember how we have often wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God together in ſinging with delight thoſe words, <hi>Pſal. 37.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. A little that a righteous man hath, is better than the riches of many wicked,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I here leave you this Letter of the counſel and advice of your aged, and loving, and faithful Father, who ſees death looking him and you in the face, and beholds <hi>the Judg before the door:</hi> this will ſpeak to you, when death hath ſilenc'd me; and it ſpeaks the ſame things which God, and Chriſt, and your own Conſciences ſpeak to you; and it ſpeaks to you (as it were) in the hearing of the world.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Put a true value on your own Beings, for ye cannot love God and Chriſt, if ye do not love your ſelves; ye are of that kind of creatures who are made much higher than all other viſible creatures, and but <hi>a little lower than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels;</hi> ye are capable to know, and chuſe, and love, and delight in God, and to ſpeak of him, and to entertain your ſelves continually with him; ye are of thoſe creatures in whoſe happineſs God glorifies all his perfections; he made this world for man; he commanded his only-begotten Son to ſacrifice himſelf for man, and ſent him
<pb facs="tcp:98500:3"/>to be born, and to live, and dye, and to riſe again, and to intercede in heaven for man; he hath reveal'd all the Truths of the Chriſtian Religion for the good of man; and therefore ye ſhould think it greater madneſs to ſell your precious ſouls and bodies to the Devil, and your luſts, for the ſhort and dirty pleaſures of ſin, than to ſell a purſe of gold, or a cabinet full of jewels for a bag of chaff or cherry-ſtones; and ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it below you to give your ſelves to any but to God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Know that as your Beings are great, ſo your happineſs or miſery will be very great; Riches or poverty, ſickneſs or health, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, or the death that deprives you of it, are things too little to make you bleſſed or miſerable; all the curſes of God, or the bleſſings of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel will be upon you preſently; and ye can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live like men, nor like Chriſtians, till ye know what it is to be ſav'd or damn'd, and what it is to loſe or enjoy God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That ye may eſcape the wrath, and obtain the glory ſet before you, let it be your chief end and intereſt to know, and honour, and enjoy God; uſe the creatures as his witneſſes, to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and declare the being and glory of God to you; for God hath not only made and appointed them to <hi>fill your hearts with food and gladneſs,</hi> but alſo that in the uſe of them ye may <hi>feel,</hi> and <hi>find,</hi> and fill your ſouls with God; but
<pb facs="tcp:98500:4"/>eſpecially behold the glory of God, as he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you in the glaſs of the Scriptures, that he may have that name in your hearts, which he hath in his word.</p>
            <p>Preſent him to your ſouls as <hi>God over all bleſſed for ever,</hi> that ye may conclude that he who is ſo infinitely good, as to be his own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, is ſufficient to make you happy: And that this God may be your eternal life and happineſs, ye muſt know and behold <hi>his glory in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>the Image of the inviſible God, the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs image of his perſon;</hi> and therefore behold his glory as the Father of ſuch a Son, and as the Lord of ſuch a ſervant, for Jeſus Chriſt is the <hi>Lords Chriſt,</hi> Luk. <hi>2.26. Chriſt is Gods, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>3.23.</hi> and executes his office of a Mediator in obedience to the will, and to the glory of God the Father, whoſe glory ye may behold in his calling him to ſuch a high office, in his accompliſhing him for the execution thereof, in proſpering him, and making him ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in his whole work, in giving him ſuch a bleſſed ſeed, in making him victorious over all his enemies, and in rewarding him for his great ſervice and obedience; ſo that according to the intent of the Scriptures forenamed, ye muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get ſuch a ſight of the glory of God ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon you in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, as will make an impreſſion of his image in your ſouls.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:4"/>
            <p>And therefore loathe and abhor ſin, which is againſt the glory of God, and which is the only evil that can make you loſe ſuch a glorious God.</p>
            <p>And for this reaſon be convinc'd of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this world, which is but a poor thing when the glory of God ſhines on your ſouls; for ye will be moſt bleſſed in him when this world ſhall be diſſolv'd and paſs'd away.</p>
            <p>And let this make Jeſus Chriſt glorious and acceptable to you, whoſe office and work it is to redeem you from all ſin and miſery, and to make you bleſſed for ever in the likeneſs and enjoyment of this glorious God.</p>
            <p>And let this alſo cauſe you to endeavour to fill all perſons with the great Name of God and Chriſt, that ye may gain them all the hearts, and love, and ſervice ye can; and therefore in all company let God and Chriſt have your good word.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Know that to love and delight in God is the beſt imployment for the days of your youth; God is much concern'd for young perſons; the Proverbs of <hi>Solomon</hi> are written, <hi>to give to the young man knowledge and diſcretion,</hi> Prov. <hi>1.4.</hi> and one great uſe of the word of God is to teach <hi>young men to cleanſe their way,</hi> Pſal. <hi>119.9. Young men, and maidens, and children,</hi> are call'd upon <hi>to praiſe the Name of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. <hi>148.12, 13.</hi> We find many mourning with holy <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:98500:5"/>they loved God ſo late, but none complaining that they loved him too ſoon; as young as you are, in heaven and hell, it's better be a young child of God, than a young child of the Devil: young Saints are the glory of God, the fulneſs and accompliſhment of Chriſt, the joy of Angels, the ſecurity and ſupport of Religion, the crown of their Parents, and the bleſſing of their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Fill your time with the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; ſee that your hearts be fill'd with grace, and then your days will be fill'd with fruit; be always receiving Chriſt, and reſigning your ſelves to him; feel your hearts continually lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold on eternal life, and live as if ye were always running to heaven; ſpend every day, ſo that ye may lye down in peace at night, that the Lords-day may be pleaſant, death gainful, and eternity glorious.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Improve Gods Ordinances of worſhip; feel your vow of Baptiſm always freſh and ſtrong upon you; feel the difference betwixt the Lords-day and other days; ſee that the word Preached be mixt with faith, ingrafted in your hearts; that it kill your ſins, and reform your lives; pray continually, and in that duty ſee that ye be with the ſpirits of children with your Father in Heaven; let all your affairs paſs through praying-hearts; and reckon all your own which ye ſincerely pray for; Sing
<pb facs="tcp:98500:5"/>Pſalms, as thoſe that make God your ſong and joy; and as if ye were ſenſible that ye are in the gates of heaven, ready to enter therein, to joyn with that world of bleſſed Angels and Saints in admiring and praiſing God. When ye come to the Lords-Supper, ſee all that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you, receive all that is offered, and do all that is commanded you.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Be ſaithful to the Truth, and then ye need not be afraid of your ſelves, or of any other: this is your greateſt ſafety, and ye may then feel the ground firm under you, and may ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. <hi>26.12. My foot ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in an even place;</hi> and if ye are called to ſuffer, chuſe it rather than ſin; and ſeeing men cannot kill your ſouls, let not the fear of them make you deſtroy them your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> Decline evil company; do not go with them to Hell, who will not go with you to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but if ye are called into ſuch company, feel your ſelves with God, whilſt ye are with them, and carry it as thoſe that are ſenſible that there is a God in the place; exerciſe thoſe graces which are contrary to, and do cendemn their ſins; be humble with the proud, meek with the angry, loving with the malicious, that they may be reproved by your graces, and that ye may not be defiled by their ſins.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> Labour to be a bleſſing to all perſons; let men ſee that in you, for which they may have
<pb facs="tcp:98500:6"/>cauſe to love and praiſe God; bear all wrongs, but do none; do what in you lyes to make all perſons holy and joyful, but make none ſinful, angry, or ſad; forgive all, but let none have need to forgive you; exerciſe their love, but do not by your ſins exerciſe their patience; give all cauſe to bleſs God for you, but give not cauſe to any to wiſh they had never known you.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> Dread debts; do not unneceſſarily bring your ſelves under the bondage of debtors; look upon it as more juſt and honourable to beg, than to borrow, if ye are not likely to pay, except in that caſe ye plainly acquaint the lender with your condition, that he may know what adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he makes; and when ye are able, pay ſeaſonably, fully, and thankfully: I would have none to lend to any children of mine, without firſt adviſing with me, except they be in a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way of trade: and my advice to ſuch of you is, that you be afraid of being too much truſted; for it's often ſeen, that they who go to the length of their credit, are injurious to others, and prove bankrupts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11.</hi> Abhor Lying: This is a ſin which is an abomination to the Lord, whom ye ſhould always pleaſe; it's contrary to the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is in every one that is born of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. <hi>It's an abuſe of your tongues</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98500:6"/>which ſhould be your glory; for the uſe of your tongues is to expreſs your minds; but in a lye your minds and thoughts do contradict your words; it's a wrong to others whom ye would have believe you, when ye do not believe your ſelves; it makes you unfit for humane ſociety; for who will converſe with thoſe whom they cannot believe; ye hereby rot your names, for a lyar is one of the worſt characters of the devil of hell; ye deſtroy your bodies and ſouls for ever, for all lyars ſhall have their part in the lake of fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12.</hi> Do not dare to ſteal; take nothing from any perſon, but what ye can ſay ye received it from the hand of God, and can praiſe him for it; and can comfortably beg his bleſſing upon it; kill thoſe luſts which ye would feed with the fruit of other mens labours; conſider, that when ye are tempted to this ſin of theft, ye are tempted to bring a curſe on your eſtates and perſons, to thruſt a dagger into your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heart, and to haſten your ſelves to an untimely and ſhameful death, and a tormenting eternity.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> Deride and jeer no perſons; let your jeſts be harmleſs, and make not your ſelves the fools of your company; but whilſt ye are cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as men and women, loſe not the ſavour of Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:7"/>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14.</hi> Haunt not Taverns or Ale-houſes, &amp;c. Go not into ſuch places, but when God calls you; ſtay no longer than he will ſtay with you; and do nothing there, but what ye ſhall have cauſe to bleſs God for when ye come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> Be thankful to them who have ſhew'd mercy and kindneſs to me and you; pray for them; inquire how it is with their poſterity; and as ye are capable, do them good: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Prov. 27.10. Thy own friend, and thy fathers friend forſake not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16.</hi> Forgive all that have done me wrong, and pray to God not to viſit it on them, or their poſterity; ye know I have had hard meaſure from ſome, and I know that <hi>I have ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God to ſpeak good for them, and to turn away his wrath from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17.</hi> As for you that are or may be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſet up for your ſelves in a way of trade: my counſel to you is this: See that your perſons be upright with God, that ye may have a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-right to the promiſes of the life that now is, and of that which is to come, which is to be prefer'd before the beſt eſtate in the world. Pray to God for his bleſſing, and ſee every cuſtomer as ſent from him, and love them as your ſelves; let all that deal with you have cauſe to ſay, that they deal with the members of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:7"/>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18.</hi> And for you that are or may be Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, my counſel and command to you is this: Let thoſe Scriptures dwell in your hearts which teach you your duty, and encourage you therein, as <hi>Epheſ. 5.5, 6, 7, 8. Col. 3.22, 23, 24, 25. Tit. 2.9, 10. 1 Pet. 2.18, 19, 20, 21.</hi> Commit them to memory, and bleſs God that he condeſcends to be a teacher of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; be content with your preſent condition, which may be the eaſieſt time of your whole age; be not apt to find fault, for that will make you uneaſie to your ſelves, and to the family; let all your words, and looks, and actions, be ſuch as do witneſs that ye do in your hearts honour your Maſters and Miſtreſſes, and Chriſt in them; bear correction patiently, though ye be wrong'd; the ſufferings of Chriſt are ſet before you as your patern herein. Pray daily for your Maſters, and their families, for ye ought to improve all your intereſt in God for their good; pray to God to fit you for your calling, that he who teacheth the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman to plow and ſow, <hi>Iſa. 28.26.</hi> may teach you herein.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Love one another according to all the Obligations that are upon you, but never put it in the power of any one to undo the other.</p>
            <p>Kill all luſtings after the honours, or riches, or pleaſures of the world: Remember I have
<pb facs="tcp:98500:8"/>told you, that as love fulfils all the Law of God, ſo luſt fulfils the law of the Devil. I will ſay no more, chuſe him for your Father that cannot dye: And as Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> ſaid to his children, ſo ſay I to you, Do not dare to meet me at the day of judgment in an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate ſtate.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June 6. 1681.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your loving and faithful Father, <hi>EDWARD LAWRENCE</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:8"/>
            <head>To all Chriſtian Parents.</head>
            <p>IT is not only for the ſake of my ſelf and children, but alſo for the ſake of you and yours that I have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed this little book; but eſpecially out of reſpect to the glory of God, that we may leave a ſeed to bleſs him in this world, when we are glorifying him in the better world; it will coſt you but a little money to buy it, and but a little time for you and your children to read it; if thoſe of you who are able, do give to every one of your children one of theſe books, and do likewiſe beſtow ſome of them upon the children of the poor, this will be no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to me; and when ye come to give your account, will be no loſs to you: I am a lover of children, and have often lifted up my heart in prayer to God for them, where I have ſeen them. I wiſh this may be a bleſſing to you and them; pray that we may leave that Religion which came
<pb facs="tcp:98500:9"/>originally from the Father of Jeſus Chriſt, and is reveal'd to us in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to our poſterity, and that they may have hearts to live according to the rules and principles of it, more than we have done. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June 6. 1681.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Servant for Jeſus ſake, <hi>EDW. LAWRENCE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 35. line 19. inſtead of <hi>cinque,</hi> read <hi>ſink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 82. line 21. read <hi>afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98500:9"/>
            <head>Parents Groans over their wicked Children.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. XVII. 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A fooliſh ſon is a grief to his father, and bitterneſs to her that bare him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is one great argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the vanity of this world, that we may be ſpoil'd of all that is dear to us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun by the ſins of other men.</p>
            <p>A common and ſad inſtance of this is, That the Comforts of godly Parents here are very much at the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their own Children: For had a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98500:10"/>good man all other delights that the creatures can yield, and <hi>did waſh his ſteps in butter, and dip his foot in oyl:</hi> Nay ſuppoſe he had all the pleaſures of Godlineſs that are ordinarily attained in this life, yet he will be a man of ſorrow, if a wicked Child make him the <hi>Father of a fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doleful caſe is preſented to us in this Text, which I have choſen for the ſubject of this diſcourſe, that I may du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affect my own and others hearts with this great calamity.</p>
            <p>In the Text two things are clearly ſet before us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A caſe taken for granted; and that is, That godly Parents have often fooliſh Children.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The miſery of that caſe is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; that is, <hi>That ſuch Children are a grief to their Fathers, and bitterneſs to the Mothers that bare them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Explication of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fooliſh ſon,</hi> that is, a wicked and ungodly ſon, or daughter; for it's uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in this book of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> that both ſexes are intended, when but one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98500:10"/>is expreſſed: Wicked Children think themſelves wiſe, wiſer than their Parents, or Maſters, or Miniſters; <hi>for vain man would be wiſe, though he be like a wild Aſſes colt,</hi> Job 11.12. But all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils children are fools; for he that will obey and imitate the Devil, who is a murderer of all his own children, and will not obey and imitate Chriſt who is the Redeemer and Saviour of all his Children, I may ſay of him in the words of a wiſe Woman, <hi>A fool is his name, and folly is with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is a grief to his Father.</hi> By Father and Mother in the Text, I underſtand a godly Father and Mother, who are moſt affected with this caſe. <hi>Is a grief:</hi> ſome render the word <hi>anger,</hi> or <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and both grief and anger are intended; for a fooliſh ſon maketh his good Father both angry and ſad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And bitterneſs to her that bare him;</hi> that is, to his good Mother, called <hi>her that bare him,</hi> to aggravate the Mothers miſery, and the Childs ſin: It cannot but torment the good Mother to think that ſhe did with ſo much ſickneſs, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98500:11"/>pain, and ſorrow bear and bring forth one that proves a child of the Devil, and is like to be a firebrand of Hell; and it's a great aggravation of the childs ſins, to imbitter the life of her that was a means of life to him; and to haſten that womb to the worms, which with ſuch pangs and throws brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world.</p>
            <p>The Text will be further opened in the following diſcourſe, which I ſhall reduce to theſe three Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it is ordinary for godly Parents to have wicked and ungodly Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That this is a very great calamity to theſe godly Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Uſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is ordinary for godly Parents to have wicked and ungodly Children: this is implied in the Text: And I may ſay of this what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.1. <hi>It is an evil which I have ſeen under the Sun, and it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this, I ſhall</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give ſome Characters of godly Parents.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98500:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. Some Characters of ungodly Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall give you ſeveral inſtances for the confirmation of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall only give you two main Characters of godly Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They are conſcienciouſly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for their preſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For the Eternal happineſs and ſalvation of their Children.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are conſcienciouſly careful for the preſervation of the natural lives of their Children, as trees ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and feed the branches that grow out of themſelves: And as it's natural to the brutes to defend and keep their own young, ſo nature it ſelf teacheth and inclineth Parents to defend, and preſerve, and provide for the fruit of their own bodies: and for this end to ſupply them with food, raiment, and phyſick, and to fit them for callings, and ſeaſonably to provide for them meet yokefellows, and every way to take care, that they neither periſh or be made miſerable: but godly Parents, in whom natural affections are ſanctified
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98500:12"/>and improved by Grace, do all theſe out of a principle of Godlineſs, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who have to do with God herein: they do it in a ſenſe of their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God, and pray for daily bread to feed their Children, and are thankful when they feel it come warm from their Father in Heaven; they do it in obedience and faithfulneſs to God; and with a deſign, that their Children may live to be born of God, and to be a bleſſing to this world, and be bleſſed in the other world: As for thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural monſters, who feed their luſts with that which ſhould maintain their Children; they are ſo far from being Godly Parents, that they are worſe than Infidels, in not providing for their Families; and are like the Devil, who (as I ſaid, is a Murderer of his own Children.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are conſcienciouſly careful for the Eternal happineſs and ſalvation of their Children; for their natural affections being now ſanctified, do work in them for the ſpiritual good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of their Children. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98500:12"/>
               <hi>I was my fathers ſon, tender and only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved in the ſight of my mother. Solomon</hi> was his fathers and mothers darling, their love did run out exceedingly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſon; and he tells us which way their love and kindneſs was expreſs'd: <hi>he taught me alſo, and ſaid unto me, Get wiſdom, get underſtanding:</hi> He tells us alſo how the affections of his good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did work, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.2, 3. <hi>What my ſon? and what the ſon of my womb? and what the ſon of my vows?</hi> The ſon of her womb, was the ſon of her vows, whom ſhe had devoted to God; thoſe Parents who have known both ſtates, the ſtate of Wrath, and the ſtate of Grace, and have experimentally felt what it is to paſs from death to life, and from the kingdom of Satan, into the kingdom of God, cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the ſame change be wrought upon their children. And as they who love themſelves with a holy love, do take God for their eternal life and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and Chriſt for their Redeemer, to redeem them from all evil, and to bring them to this happineſs; and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98500:13"/>Spirit for their Sanctifier, to fit them for this happineſs: So they that love their children with this holy Love, will deſire and endeavour that they be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with them of the ſame happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I proceed to give you three Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of ungodly Children.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are ſuch Children as will not be ſubject to the authority of their Parents: The reverence of Children to their Parents is ſo incorporated into the whole body of Religion, that all Religion is in vain without it: this fully appears, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Ye ſhall fear every man his mother, and his father, and keep my ſabbaths, I am the Lord your God.</hi> Obſerve, this duty is here joyn'd with keeping the Lords Sabbaths, wherein Religion did always very much conſiſt: but it's often ſeen, that diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children are great prophaners of the Lords-day; they are always bad, but uſually worſt on that day; and ſome of them may remember, that their firſt breaking out into ſcandalous ſins, was on the Lords-day. We are here
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98500:13"/>further taught, That this duty of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Parents, is joyn'd with all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to God; for, ſaith God in effect, it's in vain for any to pretend to call me their Lord and their God, if they do not fear their Parents; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore wicked children are numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the moſt flagitious and worſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.7. <hi>In thee have they ſet light by father and mother;</hi> they villified and deſpiſed them, and made nothing of them: ſuch break all the bonds of Religion; and many haſten through a ſhameful and untimely death, into a dreadful and tormenting eternity, whoſe wickedneſs firſt began in ſcorning and deſpiſing their Parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are ſuch children as will not obey the Commands of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: The godly Commands of Parents, are the means which God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and doth often bleſs to make the children godly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I know, Abraham, that he will command his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord to do juſtice and judgment:</hi> and God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98500:14"/>all children to obey all the holy and lawful commands of their parents, Epheſ. 6.1. <hi>Children obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right:</hi> It's the parents right that their children ſhould obey them; and it's Gods right that they ſhould obey them in the Lord: and this, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21. <hi>is well-pleaſing to the Lord:</hi> ſo that thoſe children do neither fear provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God, nor care to pleaſe him, who will not obey their parents; and ſo are children of their parents ſorrow, and of Gods wrath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are ſuch children as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful to their parents; the Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4. That it is good and acceptable before God for children <hi>to requite their parents:</hi> and they have great things for which they ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to requite their godly parents, <hi>viz.</hi> for all their care, and coſt, and pains to keep them alive, and for all their diligence and faithfulneſs in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to make them bleſſed; and all the requital which the poor parents deſire, is, that their children would but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98500:14"/>love and obey God, and not damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but theſe ungodly children are ſo far from requiting them, that like ſo many Dogs and Lyons, they tear in pieces the hearts and bowels of their tender parents.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I now come to confirm this, That it's ordinary for godly parents to have ungodly children: and for this end. I ſhall firſt give you ſome inſtances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture. 2dly, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſeveral caſes wherein this is verified.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall only give you four in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances recorded in Scripture for the confirmation hereof.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Inſtance is in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> theſe were both godly parents; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that firſt Evangelical promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. we have notice of the two great parties in the world; the one was the Woman, and her ſeed; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Serpent, and his ſeed, and of the enmity betwixt them; and though there is only mention made of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet the man is alſo included; ſo that by the woman and her ſeed, we are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98500:15"/>to underſtand <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and Chriſt and his Church; and by the Serpent, and his ſeed, are meant the Devils, and all the devils children; and foraſmuch as we find <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> of the ſame party with Chriſt and his Church, and in enmity with the Devil and his ſeed, we conclude them to be godly perſons, and godly parents: Moreover we find <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4. that they brought up their children in that Religion, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in the uſe of thoſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which he had then inſtituted as a means of their ſalvation: theſe two were the firſt-fruits of Chriſt; the firſt perſons that ever entered into the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; and Chriſt might ſay to them, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Reuben,</hi> Gen. 49.3. <hi>Ye are my firſt-born, my might, and the beginning of my ſtrength.</hi> At firſt the whole Church of God was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe two perſons, and yet theſe are the parents of that curſed and bloody <hi>Cain.</hi> And I ſhall obſerve three things in this hiſtory that render this caſe very doleful.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98500:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Eve</hi> was ſo exceeding glad for the birth of <hi>Cain:</hi> ſome are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſhe thought ſhe had brought forth the promiſed Meſſiah; and that made her break out with joy, ſaying, Gen. 4.1. <hi>I have gotten a man from the Lord:</hi> and yet this is he of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. <hi>He was of that wicked one, meaning the devil:</hi> This is a common caſe, that parents are exceedingly glad for the birth of a child, and call their friends and neighbours to rejoyce with them; and yet that ſweet and pleaſant babe proves the greateſt torment to their parents, which ever they met with in their whole age.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider his crime, he barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly murdered his own brother, Gen. 4.8. <hi>Cain roſe up againſt Abel his brother, and ſlew him:</hi> He conſidered not how this would grieve the heart of his good Father and Mother, nor that he was the elder brother, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to have nouriſhed the life of the younger, and to have been a pattern of holineſs and love to him; neither did he conſider that he hated
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98500:16"/>and murder'd not only a brother, but alſo a holy child of God, and for that which he ought to have honoured and loved him; becauſe <hi>his brothers works were righteous:</hi> and he conſidered not how his brothers blood would cry to God for vengeance againſt him; no bonds, or arguments, or reaſons will prevail with ungodly children.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the dreadful judgment of God, both upon himſelf and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: Gods judgment on his ſoul was ſo dreadful, that he deſperately cries out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Mine ini quity is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that it may be forgiven:</hi> he was caſt out of the favour of God, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated from the Church, and all his poſterity were excluded from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion therewith: they are call'd the ſons and daughters of men, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Sons of God, and at laſt all periſhed in the deluge of waters; and yet, I ſay, this bloody and curſed monſter was the ſon, the eldeſt ſon of the two firſt godly parents that ever were in the world.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98500:16"/>
            <p n="2">2d Inſtance is in <hi>Noah;</hi> the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was in the firſt godly man in <hi>the old world,</hi> as the ages before the flood are called, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. This inſtance is in the beſt man in the new World after the flood: this <hi>Noah</hi> hath a great cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter in the Scriptures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.8, 9. <hi>Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord. Noah was a juſt man, and perfect in his generations.</hi> When all the earth was debauch'd and corrupt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11, 12. yet then was <hi>Noah juſt and upright, and walked with God,</hi> it's he that is called in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>A preacher of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:</hi> It is he that was ſo much in the favour of God, that he and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily were ſingled out to be preſerved in the Ark, when all the world beſides were drown'd and periſh'd in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: yet this holy <hi>Noah</hi> was the Father of that wicked <hi>Ham,</hi> whom all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Noah</hi> (as the Scripture calls that deluge) were not effectual to eure of his wickedneſs; but he went a wicked man into the Ark, and came wicked out; inſomuch that his own holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was inſpired by a prophetical ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98500:17"/>to curſe both his ſon and poſterity, and the crime mentioned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22, 25. was his irreverence and diſreſpect to his father.</p>
            <p n="3">3d Inſtance is in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, who ſo greatly feared God, that his ſon <hi>Jacob</hi> gives God that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable name, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.42. <hi>The fear of Iſaac,</hi> meaning the God whom <hi>Iſaac</hi> feared; yet he and that good mother <hi>Rebekkah</hi> were the parents of a wicked <hi>Eſau,</hi> whom God is ſaid to hate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. I know we read <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.28. that <hi>Iſaac loved Eſau:</hi> but we ſee that children may be greatly beloved of their parents, and yet abhorred and curſed of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4th Inſtance is in <hi>David,</hi> call'd a man after Gods own heart, whom God rais'd up to be king of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> he was a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of a conſiderable part of the holy Scriptures; ſuch an eminent type of Chriſt, that Chriſt himſelf is often call'd <hi>David</hi> in Scripture; yet he was the tender father of that wicked <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who bloodily murdered his brother <hi>Amnon,</hi> and miſerably and ſhamefully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98500:17"/>dyed in Treaſon and Rebellion againſt his Royal Father, whoſe bitter lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is yet in our ears, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33. <hi>O my ſon Abſolom, my ſon, my ſon Abſolom! would God I had died for thee; O Abſolom my ſon, my ſon!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, I ſhall further inſtance in four Caſes, wherein this is often verified.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe Children who are moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of their parents, do often prove the moſt wicked Children. <hi>Abſolom</hi> was <hi>David</hi>'s darling; inſomuch, that although he ſet his whole kingdom in a flame, and conſtrained his father to fly for his life; yet when <hi>David</hi> ſent out his Army to ſuppreſs that rebellion, he gives this charge to his Commanders, in the audience of the Soldiers, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.5. <hi>Deal gently for my ſake with the young man, even with Abſolom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it often happens, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who have moſt of their Parents love and delight, and whoſe looks and talk they are moſt taken with, and whom they are moſt apt to boaſt of, and are moſt unwilling to part with,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98500:18"/>and in whom they promiſe themſelves moſt content and pleaſure, do often prove the greateſt ſcourge and torment to their parents; for it is not the love of the godly parents, but the love of God that makes children holy and happy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is often the ſad caſe of ſome holy Miniſters of the Word: I know it's a Popiſh and peeviſh humour in ſome to ſay, that Miniſters children ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do well; indeed every thing of Miniſters is moſt expoſed to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of people, and therefore the wickedneſs of their children is moſt obſerv'd and talk'd of; but the holy, learned, and every-way proſperous and bleſſed ſeed of divers godly Miniſters, is ſufficient to confute and ſhame the ignorance of people herein; and yet it is true that many godly Miniſters in all ages have groan'd under this ſad ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity: <hi>Eli</hi> was a holy Prieſt of God, but his two ſons were Devils incarnate, monſters of men, ſcandalous, ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and adulterous ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98500:18"/>appears 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. And this is no rare thing, that the Prayers, Studies, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Examples of many good Miniſters are often made ſucceſsful to bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to Heaven, when they can by no means reſtrain their own children from running to Hell, and their own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren make them do the work of their Miniſtry with grief, when often the children of drunkards, worldlings, and whoremongers will be their crown and glory in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is often true, when both pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are godly; indeed when either father or mother is wicked, no marvel if the children be hardned in their ſins by their examples: but it's uſually ſeen, that when children have both <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the father, and alſo the law of the mother;</hi> and when they cry to all the Miniſters and Chriſtians about them, to help them by their prayers and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to ſave their children; yet all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail not, but the holy father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſcarce keep one anothers hearts from being broken by their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98500:19"/>ſtubborn and diſobedient children.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The children of godly parents often prove wicked, when God doth ſanctifie, and bleſs, and ſave the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ungodly parents; we ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times trees of righteouſneſs, growing in the families of the wicked, when briars and thorns grow up in the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the righteous: We read <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. that <hi>Ahaz,</hi> a very wicked king, begat holy <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> who was an Idolater of the higheſt rate; a Witch, and ſuch a bloody murderer, that the Chronicle of his reign tells us, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.16. <hi>He ſhed innocent blood very much, till he had filled Jeruſalem from one end to the other</hi> (though afterwards he is ſet forth to be the greateſt pattern of the grace of God in the Old Teſtament, as <hi>Paul</hi> is in the New Teſtament): It is no new ſight to ſee children of the beſt Saints in the way to Hell, and children of Atheiſts and Perſecutors in the way to Heaven; Nay, though ſome parents do perſecute their own children for loving
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98500:19"/>and fearing God, yet they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch them; when all endeavours of godly parents will not prevail to make their children hate ſin, and love God: and this is one of the ſaddeſt inſtances of that great myſtery of Providence, mentioned <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.14. <hi>There he juſt men, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked: again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the work of the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Head.</hi> It is a very great calamity to godly parents to have wicked and ungodly children; <hi>A fooliſh ſon</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>is a grief to his father, and bitterneſs to her that bare him:</hi> To the ſame purpoſe is that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.21. <hi>He that begetteth a fool, doth it to his ſorrow, and the father of a fool hath no joy;</hi> a fooliſh ſon damps all his joy: and <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.13. <hi>A fooliſh ſon is the calamity of his father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſet forth the greatneſs of this trouble by theſe Eight particulars:</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98500:20"/>
            <p n="1">1. By the matter of theſe parents grief.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the paſſions that this calamity doth move and affect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By comparing this with other afflictions, and ſhewing how this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By ſhewing that this makes theſe parents do all their work with grief and ſorrow.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By ſhewing that this embitters all their other comforts.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the ſad concommitants of it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By the ſeveral aggravations of it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. By inſtancing in ſome caſes wherein this calamity is more grievous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The matter of theſe parents grief is very ſad, as appears in theſe ſeven things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That their children are ſo defiled and debauched with ſin, which is ſo loathſome to theſe holy parents; it vexed the righteous ſoul of <hi>Lot</hi> to ſee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98500:20"/>and hear the filthy converſation of the beaſtly <hi>Sodomites;</hi> how grievous then muſt it be to theſe godly parents, to ſee and hear the filthineſs of their own dear children; it is a grievous thing to a man that loves God, and Godlineſs, and Souls, to ſee a drunkard ſtaggering in the ſtreets, or to hear any man blaſpheming and reproaching his Maker and Redeemer; but none can tell but thoſe that feel it, what a ſad ſpectacle it is to ſober and godly parents to ſee their own children drunk; or how it torments them to hear their own children lying, and blaſpheming God and his Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That their children are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil, and under the power of Satan, and ridden by him, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captive by him at his will; it was a lamentable caſe of that good Mother, who came to Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Have mercy upon me, O Lord, thou ſon of David, my daughter is grievouſly vexed with a devil:</hi> yet this was not her daughters ſin, but only her great affliction: but how doleful is it to theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98500:21"/>parents, who have renounced the devil themſelves, and live in continual war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare with him, to ſee the hearts, and mouths, and lives of the children, whom they have devoted to God, fill'd and poſſeſs'd with the devil, whoſe children they are, and whoſe luſts they will do; if the devil tempt the parents, their own graces will reſiſt and overcome his temptations; but they cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their children from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and from falling into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the devil; but with ſad hearts do ſee the Lyon of Hell running away with the lambs of their flock, and cannot recover them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That their children are under the wrath and curſe of God; it did ſadly affect the father of that lunatick ſon, mentioned <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.15. to ſee his ſon <hi>fall oft into the fire, and oft into the water:</hi> How would he ſcreech at ſuch a ſight, and cry, Ah my dear child will be burnt, my child will be drown'd! but much more terrible is it to theſe parents, who know the terrors of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98500:21"/>Lord, to know that their children have cut off the entail of the Covenant of Grace, and are every moment ready to fall into the hands of the living God! when ſuch parents are, with faith, reading the curſes of Gods Law, how doth it cut them to the heart to think, that they are then reading their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens doom.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That their children are under thoſe black characters, which are given in Scripture to ungodly men; for the faith of theſe parents makes all perſons have that name in their hearts, which they have in the Word: And as God is no reſpecter of perſons, ſo Faith, ſo far as it prevails, reſpecteth not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of any, no not of a mans own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but becauſe they are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their notice and obſervation than others, and becauſe they are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for them, therefore the deeper impreſſions do theſe characters make on their hearts; ſo that this is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of theſe parents, that whileſt they look on perſons through the glaſs of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98500:22"/>the Scriptures, and ſee many to be the jewels, and treaſure, and children, and heirs of God, and the glorious bride and ſpouſe of Chriſt; they muſt and do judge their own wicked children to be a generation of vipers, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and dogs, and ſwine, and lyons, and bears, and wolves, as God calls them in his Word.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the anger and diſpleaſure of God appears ſo much againſt theſe good parents herein; indeed the ſenſe of their own folly muſt make them juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God in this ſharp correction, and cauſe them to ſay with <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 26.3. As it is meet that there be <hi>a whip for the horſe, and a bridle for the aſſe;</hi> ſo is it, that there be <hi>a rod for the fools back:</hi> But this is very grievous, that God ſhould correct them with a ſcourge made of their own bowels, and ſhould chaſten a bleſſed father with a curſed child; his holy anger muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged herein; for when the child de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth his father, God himſelf doth juſtly ſpit in the fathers face.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98500:22"/>
            <p n="6">6. The ſhame and diſgrace which comes to them hereby, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.26. <hi>He that waſteth his father, and chaſeth away his mother, is a ſon that cauſeth ſhame:</hi> Every one will be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon their parents, and to ſay, Surely theſe children were never taught to ſerve God, who do ſo ſacrifice them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſervice of the devil.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Both parents are deeply affected for the trouble and miſery that comes hereby to one another; their love to, and ſympathy with one another, makes the burden of both more uneaſie: The good father is not only troubled with a wicked child, but alſo for the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſorrow of his wife; and the good mother is not only troubled with the wicked child, but alſo for the grief of her husband; the mothers heart bleeds to ſee the tears, and to hear the groans of the afflicted father, and cries out, Oh, what a child have I brought forth, that ſo much deprives me of the comfort of a loving hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and is like to break his heart,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98500:23"/>and to make me a deſolate and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate widow: The father mourns to ſee the tears, and the ſad countenance, and to hear the groans of the diſtreſſed mother; and is ready to cry out, Wo is me, that the child of my bowels is deſtroying the wife of my boſom; and yet theſe hard-hearted children are not affected herewith; but let the parents ſigh, they will ſing; let the parents weep and mourn, they will rant and roar; and care no more to break their parents hearts, than to break a Tobacco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe; and will not abate a lie, or oath, or cup, to ſave the lives of their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The greatneſs of this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity appears by the paſſions in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, which are moved and affected hereby. I ſhall only inſtance in three paſſions, Fear, Anger, and Sorrow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Fear:</hi> This is a troubleſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and godly parents are never out of fear of their wicked children; they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98500:23"/>are afraid that every one that knocks at the door, and that every poſt, and every friend that comes to viſit them, brings them ſome ſad tidings of their diſobedient children. I ſhall amplifie this, by inſtancing in three great Evils, which ſuch parents are greatly perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the fear of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are afraid leſt their children are in the practice of ſome great ſins: this was <hi>Jobs</hi> fear, when his children were feaſting together, <hi>Job</hi> 1.5. <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, It <hi>may be my ſons have ſinn'd and curs'd God in their hearts:</hi> their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are ſeldom out of their ſight, but the good parents are in fear of this; they know their children are always expos'd to the devils temptations, and to the ſnares of the world, and to the allurements of evil company; and that their corrupt hearts are ſet to comply with all; and that they have provoked God to give them up to their own luſts; and therefore they are in continual fear, leſt theſe poor children are lying, or ſwearing, or curſing, or whoring, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98500:24"/>drunk, and defiling, and debauching, and deſtroying themſelves and others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are in fear leſt ſome heavy judgment of God will befall them in this life: And thus <hi>David,</hi> when his ſon <hi>Abſolom</hi> was in the head of a high rebellion againſt his father, and the battel was to be fought with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, was fearful leſt his ſon ſhould then periſh in his ſins: theſe parents know that their poor children are out of Gods way, and <hi>as birds wandring from the neſt,</hi> Prov. 27.8. are expos'd to all manner of danger; they know what the word threatens againſt them, and what fearful inſtances there are of the vengeance of God upon diſobedient children; and therefore they are in fear, leſt their ſins ſhould bring them to ſome untimely, and ſhameful death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are in fear of their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation; they are ſenſible that their children <hi>are children of wrath,</hi> and do live in thoſe ſins <hi>for which the wrath of God comes on the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98500:24"/>and theſe parents believe what Hell is; for as faith in the promiſes is the ſubſtance of things hoped for; ſo faith, as it believes the threatnings, is the ſubſtance of things feared; and therefore they cannot but tremble to think, that their dear lambs, whom they ſo tenderly nouriſh'd and cheriſh'd, are in danger every moment to be caſt into the fire that is prepared for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anger</hi> is another paſſion that is moved in godly parents, with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of their children: and this is troubleſome; for a man is never out of trouble whilſt he is in anger; and the more the wills of theſe parents are bent to have their children godly, the more are they diſpleas'd, and provok'd to anger by their ſins: they are angry to ſee them provoke that God whom they themſelves are ſo careful to pleaſe; and to ſee them deſtroying their precious ſouls, which they are labouring to ſave; and to ſee them waſte thoſe eſtates on their filthy luſts, which they have got
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98500:25"/>by their care, and labour, and prayers: they cannot but think of them with anger, and ſpeak of them with anger, and look at them with anger: and thus their children which ſhould be their delight and pleaſure, are a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual croſs and vexation to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sorrow:</hi> They are deeply affected with grief and ſorrow for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their children; the parents graces cauſe them to mourn for their childrens ſins; their ſaving-knowledge makes their hearts bleed to ſee their children ſcorn and deſpiſe that glory which they ſee in God and Chriſt; and whilſt they by faith are feeding on Chriſt, it grieves them to ſee their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren feeding themſelves with the dirty pleaſures of ſin; their love to God makes them groan, that their children love ſin the worſt evil, and hate God the chiefeſt good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I proceed to ſhew the greatneſs of this calamity, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it with other troubles, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98500:25"/>how this exceeds them. I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in four other Troubles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is a greater calamity than to be without Children; ſo that if God had ſaid of thoſe Parents, as he ſaid of him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.30. <hi>Write ye this man, and this woman childleſs,</hi> the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had not been ſo great, as to be afflicted with wicked children: ſuch parents may ſay with our Saviour in another caſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.29. <hi>Bleſſed are the barren, and the wombs that never bare, and the paps which never gave ſuck.</hi> As it's better to have no herbs in your gardens, than to have only ſtinking-weeds that cumber the ground; and better to have no beaſts in your ground, than a company of foxes and wolves; ſo it's better to have no children, than to have only ſuch who are the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſhame, and plague, and torment of their parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's a greater miſery than to have diſeaſed, or deformed children: This indeed is a ſore affliction, to be the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98500:26"/>of ſick, or blind, or lame, or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous children, becauſe ſuch children are naturally diſabled to do that ſervice to God, and their generation, and their parents, which otherwiſe they might do: but this is not ſo grievous as to have wicked children; for they that are moſt diſeaſed and uncomely, are often called to be the bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious children and heirs of God, and the amiable and beautiful bride and ſpouſe of Chriſt, when all wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are the filthy and loathſome chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the devil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is more grievous than the death of children. I know it's matter of deep ſorrow when parents may ſay with the tender Patriarch, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.36. <hi>Joſeph is not, and Simeon is not:</hi> My ſon is dead, and is not; and my dear daughter is dead, and is not; but this ſorrow is not laſting, the impreſſion of it uſually doth, and ſhould wear off; but wicked children are conſtant trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to their parents, and cauſe them to ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.10.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98500:26"/>
               <hi>My days are ſpent with grief, and my years with ſighing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This calamity is greater than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution from wicked men, though that be alſo very grievous; inſomuch that <hi>Paul,</hi> a man of a great ſpirit, was ſo affected herewith, that he ſolemnly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeecheth the <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.30. <hi>For the Lord Jeſus ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that they would ſtrive together with him in prayer to God for him,</hi> to deliver him from perſecuting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; it is a ſad caſe to be ſmitten and wounded in our names by lying and ſlanderous tongues: <hi>David,</hi> and Chriſt in him, tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.20. That <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach hath broken his heart:</hi> It is ſad for the jewels of God to be accounted and uſed as the ſink and jakes of the world, and to have our eſtates waſted and ſpoyl'd, and to be expos'd to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery and want, and to be drag'd from our healthful and pleaſant habitations and families, and to be caſt among rogues and thieves into naſty and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome priſons, and to have our innocent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98500:27"/>and precious blood ſhed by barbarous men: but all this is not ſo grievous as to be tormented by wicked children; for in that caſe we are diſtreſſed by the ſins of our enemies; and if ſo, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12. <hi>We could have born it:</hi> But in this caſe we are afflicted by the ſins of our own children, and may ſay with <hi>David,</hi> when he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled by <hi>Shimei,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.11. <hi>Behold my ſon which came forth of my bowels, ſeeketh my life: how much more may this Benjamite?</hi> It is a far greater torment to have the children of our own bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els tear and break our hearts, than to be deſtroy'd by mercileſs enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The greatneſs of this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity is ſeen, in that it cauſeth theſe good parents to do all their work with ſorrow. I ſhall inſtance in three ſorts of Works which they do in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Souls: 1. Natural. 2. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. 3. Religious Works. He that hath a wicked child on his heart, doth all theſe with a ſad heart.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98500:27"/>
            <p n="1">1. Natural Works: theſe they do with ſorrow: <hi>They are fed with the bread of tears, and drink their tears in great meaſure,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks in another caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.5. And as it's ſaid, in <hi>the prayer of the afflicted,</hi> Pſal. 102.9. <hi>They eat aſhes like bread, and mingle their drink with weeping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They do their Civil Works with grief: this makes them labour with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in their particular callings; it was <hi>Solomons</hi> trouble to think that <hi>a fool ſhould have the rule of his labour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he laboured, and ſhewed himſelf wiſe under the Sun,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.18, 19, 20. And this ſad caſe is often obſerv'd, that the ſame eſtates which were the fruit of the wiſe and good parents prayers, and diligence, are conſum'd upon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens luſts; and that the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which were a bleſſing to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and wherewith they did honour God, and feed Chriſt in his members, do prove a curſe to their children, and weapons in their hands wherewith they ſight againſt God and his people.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98500:28"/>
            <p n="3">3. This alſo cauſeth them to do their Religious Works in grief and ſorrow. I ſhall only inſtance in two particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This makes them inſtruct theſe poor ungodly children with ſorrow: It is a doleful caſe when men can have their dogs to come at their whiſtle, and their horſes to yield to the bridle, and their oxen to ſubmit to the yoke; but their unruly children will not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the holy government of their parents; they can readily learn filthy words, and wicked actions from their ungodly School-fellows, or Fellow-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, or debauch'd companions; but they will not hear the inſtruction of their father, nor obey the law of their mother.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This cauſeth them to pray for ſuch children with ſorrow; for accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as is the ſpiritual ſtate of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo are their holy parents affected in prayer to God for them; when they can in prayer call upon God as the Father of their children, and can
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98500:28"/>preſent their children to God as ſuch, who are born of God, and adopted of him, and can beg mercy for them who are the veſſels of mercy, then they do, as the Apoſtle for the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 1.4. <hi>In every prayer make requeſt for them with joy:</hi> but when children are manifeſtly wicked, and their good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents muſt in prayer to God call them what they are, and muſt ſay, Lord, my poor children are children of the devil, children of diſobedience, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thy wrath, lying, ſwearing, covetous, drunken, unclean, ſtubborn children; Oh pity, pardon, ſave, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them; they pray for them, but they pray in the ſorrow and anguiſh of their ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I come to ſhew how wicked children embitter all the comforts of their good parents; ſo that as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.21. <hi>A father of a fool hath no joy.</hi> I ſhall exemplifie this in four particulars.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98500:29"/>
            <p n="1">1. The good parents cannot be ſo comfortable and delightful to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they would be, when both are in bitterneſs for their wicked children; the husband cannot be ſuch a comfort to his wife, when he is almoſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual anger and ſorrow for his wicked child; nor the wife ſuch a delight to her husband, when her heart is bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her ungodly child; for if they have no joy in themſelves, as was ſaid before, they cannot be ſo much the joy and delight of one another: but when they lye down, this makes them water their bed with tears, and they awake with ſorrow, with a wicked child on their hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They cannot take ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as they would in the other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are godly; not that they love them leſs, but rather more; but their joy in them is much interrupted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. Suppoſe among many children there be but one ungodly child, that one is a diſturbance and annoyance to the whole family; that one ſinner (as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98500:29"/>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks in a more general caſe) deſtroys much good; it grieves them to think, that whereas that one child was in the ſame Covenant, and had the ſame dedication to God by Baptiſm, and the ſame affection and education from the parents with all the other children; yet the reſt are veſſels of mercy, but this ſeems to be a veſſel of wrath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They cannot take ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the victory over their own ſins, when they ſee the ſame corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which are abhorred, and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and forſaken by the parents, breaking out, and reigning in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This interrupts their joy in God and Jeſus Chriſt; when ſuch parents muſt with the ſame faith believe Gods wrath to their children, as they believe his love to themſelves; and when they look upon God as their Father, they muſt look upon him as an enemy to their Children; and when they ſay, We hope Heaven is our portion and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98500:30"/>place, it muſt grieve them that their children will not go with them thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The greatneſs of this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction appears further by the concommi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of it. I ſhall only inſtance in three things that uſually accompany it, which make it more grievous.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such children do often impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh their parents; <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that a wicked child <hi>waſteth his father, and chaſeth away his mother;</hi> ſuch children care not if they ſtarve their poor pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſo that they can feed their own luſts; and it's often ſeen, that a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eſtate is conſum'd by riotous chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such children do often debauch and corrupt the other children, and make their brethren in nature, to be their <hi>brethren in iniquity:</hi> and often their brothers and ſiſters are eaſier in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed to ſin by a wicked brother, than drawn to God by a godly father: and if any of the other children be godly,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98500:30"/>theſe wicked ones do hate, and revile, and perſecute them like wicked <hi>Cain,</hi> who ſlew his brother becauſe his works were righteous.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They bring reproach upon that good Religion which their good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents profeſs and practiſe: and thus <hi>Eli</hi>'s ſons made men <hi>abhor the offerings of the Lord;</hi> and with ſome the holy lives of the parents cannot wipe off the reproach which is caſt on Religion by the wickedneſs of their children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> The greatneſs of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction appears by theſe eight Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It aggravates their grief to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what pleaſure and delight theſe children were to them in their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; it torments them now to ſee their ſweet and pleaſant ſmiles, turn'd into ſcornful and diſdainful looks at their parents, and their pretty broken words turn'd into oaths and lies, and other rotten ſpeeches; and to think
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98500:31"/>that theſe who once were ſo forward to claſp about their necks, and to kiſs them, and to run at their commands, do now <hi>lift up the heel againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It aggravates their ſorrow to ſee themſelves ſo miſerably diſappointed in their former hopes of theſe children; <hi>Hope deferred</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>makes the heart ſick:</hi> but to be croſs'd and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in hopes of ſo great mercy, doth even break the heart. When theſe parents remember how pleaſant it was to them to hear theſe children liſp out their Catechiſms, and to hear their good words of God and Chriſt; it cannot but be very grievous to them, that the ſame children which they did with <hi>Hannah</hi> lend to the Lord, ſhould ſell themſelves to the devil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It aggravates their ſorrow, that their children are ſo void of love to their parents, and to ſee that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of lyars, and drunkards, and whoremongers, and thieves, is more delightful to them than the company of their parents.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98500:31"/>
            <p n="4">4. It aggravates their ſorrow to look upon the holy children of others; when they may ſay, Yonder are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that make a glad father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the children of our bodies, and counſels, and prayers, and vows, and tears, live as if their father was an <hi>Amorite,</hi> and their mother an <hi>Hittite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Aggravation is, in caſe the parents have but one child, and that proves fooliſh and diſobedient: and of this there be many inſtances; the Scripture, to ſet forth the ſaddeſt kind of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, compares it to the mourning for an only ſon, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.26. <hi>Make thee mourning as for an only ſon, moſt bitter lamentation.</hi> Zech. 12.10. <hi>They ſhall mourn as one that mourneth for an only ſon.</hi> I know theſe Scriptures ſpeak of parents mourning for the death of an only ſon; but it's not ſo ſad to follow an only ſon to the grave, as to ſee an only child live to the diſhonour of God, to be a curſe to his generation, and to be continually deſtroying his precious ſoul; it's a very bitter caſe, when as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98500:32"/>much love, and kindneſs, and care, and coſt, and pains, and prayers, and faſtings, are beſtowed upon one child, as other parents beſtow upon many children; and notwithſtanding all this, one child ſhould prove ſuch a monſter of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if the ſins of many ungodly chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren met in him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Aggravation. When Gods holy Miniſters are the Fathers of fools, which (I have told you) often happens: and this is a moſt dreadful caſe for ſuch who have <hi>the keys of the kingdom of heaven,</hi> and yet muſt bind over their own children to the wrath of God: ſuch know <hi>the terrors of the Lord,</hi> and the torments of Hell more than others; and therefore muſt be more affected to believe, that this at preſent is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own children.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Aggravation. When ſuch chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom their parents deſign'd to ſerve God in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, do prove ungodly: this is matter of great lamentation, for the parents to intend them for the higheſt office in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98500:32"/>the Church, and give them education for that end, that theſe children ſhould make themſelves as <hi>ſalt without ſavour, which is good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and trodden under foot of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Aggravation. When children are a grief to their parents in their old age, and do as it were throw dirt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hoary heads, which is their <hi>crown of glory;</hi> it's the command of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.22. <hi>Deſpiſe not thy mother when ſhe is old: Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. That the days of old age are <hi>evil days;</hi> their very age is a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and incurable diſeaſe; now the <hi>graſhopper,</hi> every light thing is a burden to them, and therefore it muſt be more troubleſome to them to be then tormented with wicked children, when <hi>the ſtrong men</hi> (as Divines think) <hi>Solomon</hi> calls the legs, do bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their children who ſhould be a ſtaff and ſupport to them, do break their hearts, and cauſe their grey-hairs to go with ſorrow to the grave.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98500:33"/>
            <p>I now come to make application of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Let ſuch parents praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, whom God hath bleſs'd with wiſe, and holy, and obedient children; whether by thoſe words in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.12. <hi>David</hi> means children accompliſh'd with natural or ſpiritual endowments, or both, I ſhall not determine; but to apply them to the caſe in hand, I ſay it's the great mercy of God to you, that when ſo many children are as noiſome weeds, your ſons ſhould be as hopeful <hi>plants grown up in their youth;</hi> and when ſo many make themſelves ugly, and deform'd with ſin, <hi>your daughters ſhould be as corner-ſtones</hi> (in which is ſeen the beauty of the building, and the art and skill of the workman) <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed after the ſimilitude of a palace.</hi> Do not hence conclude, that you are better parents than others, or have had more care in the education of your children than others, but aſcribe all to the free grace of God, <hi>who will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98500:33"/>have mercy upon whom he will have mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let none preſume to cenſure godly parents for their wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; <hi>To him that is afflicted,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, pity ſhould be ſhew'd him from his friend.</hi> Have they not trouble enough already, but will you add to their affliction? They have not hereby forfeited the good thoughts and eſteem which you ſhould have of them; and if you judge them for this, ye muſt judge as wiſe and holy Saints of God as ever were in the world; though God herein doth ſharply correct them, yet he will not allow you to ſit in judgment, and to paſs ſentence upon them: I ſay to you, as <hi>Job</hi> to his friends, <hi>Hold your peace, let them alone;</hi> and leave them to ſtand or fall to their own Maſter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſhould fill the hearts of theſe holy parents with revenge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sin and Satan, which have ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98500:34"/>debauch'd, and defiled, and deſtroy'd their dear children: If a man ſhould murder your child, a ſpirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge would riſe in you, and you would ſay to ſuch a one, I will have thy life and blood for the life and blood of my child; but Sin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan have deſtroy'd both the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoul and body of the child; therefore labour, as for other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo for this alſo, to be reveng'd of them: Labour to do as <hi>David</hi> did by the Lyon and the Bear, which took a Lamb out of his flock, he ſlew both the Lyon and the Bear, and delivered the Lamb; ſo do all ye can to reſeue your poor lambs out of the jaws of Satan; however labour to hate Sin and Satan more, to promote Gods honour and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the ſalvation of ſouls more: and this is the way to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on Sin and Satan for the ruine of your children.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98500:34"/>
            <p n="4">4. I do hence exhort all holy and obedient children to acknowledge the grace of God to them, that they are or have been the joy and crown of their parents: It is his diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing grace that made you to differ from all wicked children, and perhaps from ſome that came out of the ſame womb, and ſucked the ſame mothers breaſts as you did. Conſider four things which are great matter of praiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ye are the children of holy parents; that ye may comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably come to God in prayer, and ſay, we are the children of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant our father; we are thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and the children of thy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid our mother: bleſs God for your parents good counſels and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and for a great part of an age of prayers, which ye are daily receiving the benefit of; if your parents are dead, and in heaven, it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98500:35"/>may put you into a holy and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual frame to think of the graces of God that did ſhine in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the ſame graces which dwelt in your good parents, are in you: <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of it as matter of praiſe to God, that the ſame faith was in <hi>Timothy,</hi> which dwelt firſt in his Grandmother <hi>Lois,</hi> and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eunice;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> rejoyced greatly, that he found the children of the elect Lady walking in truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That thou art freed from thoſe ſtings of conſcience, which grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs children ſhall one day feel for their diſobedience to their parents; thou mayeſt joyfully reflect, that thou waſt the joy of thy holy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and that their lives have been made ſweeter, and their croſſes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier by thee; that thou art the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſeal of their holy education, when wicked children are the ſhame and reproach of their parents.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98500:35"/>
            <p n="4">4. That thou haſt a right to that rich and precious promiſe annext to the fifth Commandment, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2, 3. So that thou may'ſt be aſſur'd that it <hi>ſhall go well with thee</hi> both in this world, and in the world to come; I do ſeriouſly profeſs, I had rather have a right to that one promiſe made to obedient children, than to the beſt eſtate and inheritance under the Sun.</p>
            <p>I ſhall finiſh this diſcourſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In preſcribing ſome means to be us'd by thoſe that may be, or are parents, to prevent this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall direct thoſe parents that groan under this calamity, how to bear it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall give a ſerious exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to ſuch children who are the grief and bitterneſs of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98500:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall preſcribe means to be us'd to prevent this calamity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Uſe all holy prudence and care in your choice of a yoke-fellow; for if ye make your ſelves the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands or wives of fools, ye are like in time to become the fathers or mothers of fools; when before the flood, the members of Gods Church married with a wicked generation, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6.2. they brought forth a wicked poſterity; but to have a holy yoke-fellow, is the way to have a holy ſeed; and therefore what ye would moſt deſire to have for your ſelves, that labour to find in the perſon who is to be one fleſh with you: thou wouldſt have thy ſelf born of God; thou wouldſt have the Image of God, and the life of Chriſt in thy ſelf. Labour that theſe things be in the perſon whom thou chuſeſt for thy yoke-fellow; but never make choice of one for
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98500:36"/>thy husband or wife, whom thou ſhouldſt not chuſe for thy compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be faithful and upright with God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.7. <hi>The juſt man walketh in his integrity, and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are bleſſed after him:</hi> If you would have grace and mercy for your children, love and pleaſe the God of all grace and mercy; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſecret ſins are in thee, kill thoſe ſins for thy poor childrens ſake, leſt the ſins you too much harbour in your own hearts, do break out in your childrens lives: Parents may often ſee their own ſins againſt their heavenly father in their childrens diſobedience to them; when your children deſpiſe you, remember your want of honour, and fear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of God; when they vex and trouble you, remember how ye have griev'd and provoked him; when they decline your company, remember how your hearts have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98500:37"/>wandered from God in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Bewail and beg pardon of God for your failings heretofore to your parents; for many do often reap from their own children, what they formerly ſow'd by their ſins againſt their parents; and their miſcarriages to their parents do fall upon them in the wickedneſs of their children: the beſt may ſadly reflect upon their want of due honour, and obedience, and thankfulneſs to their parents; ye may remember your peeviſh looks, undecent behaviour to them; your grieving them in quarrelling with your brethren and ſiſters; your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt cenſuring them for partiality in their love to their children, and judging them to want love to you, when you were wanting in your duty to them; and many, who are now godly parents themſelves, may remember, that by greater ſins in their youth they were the grief and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98500:37"/>bitterneſs of their fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and therefore pray mightily to God to pardon you, and not to viſit theſe ſins upon you in the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of your children.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Pray to God not to viſit your ſins upon your children: When <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was in Heaven, <hi>Amon</hi> his ſon followed the ſteps of his uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted eſtate; and <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captive into <hi>Babylon</hi> for the ſins of <hi>Manaſſeh:</hi> Pray that your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may not be like you in any thing, wherein ye are unlike God; and that <hi>their teeth may not be ſet on edg for the ſowre grapes that ye have eaten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Be deeply affected with the corruption of nature in your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: For as no man will value a Saviour for himſelf, who is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the ſin and miſery which he muſt be ſaved from; ſo ye muſt be ſenſible of your childrens ſins, or elſe ye cannot labour for their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98500:38"/>When your ſweet babes are born, ye rejoyce to find that in Gods book all their members were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; but ye ſhould alſo be ſenſible of that body of ſin they are born with, and that by nature they are young Atheiſts, and Infidels, and haters of God, and baſphemers, and whoremongers, and lyars, and thieves, and murderers; for they are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclin'd to theſe and all other fins, and are by nature children of the wrath of the infinite God; and being convinc'd of this, ye will find that your chief care of them ſhould be to ſave them from this dreadful ſtate of ſin and miſery.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Be convinc'd what a great deal of work lies upon you to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ſalvation of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: young children always make a great deal of work; they make work for parents, and work for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and work for all that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them; but to ſave them from
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98500:38"/>ſin and hell, is the greateſt work that belongs to their parents: for this purpoſe they have a great deal a work to do in their own hearts; they muſt know, and believe, and love, and obey the doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation themſelves, that they may be able, and ſit to inſtruct their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren therein; for a man cannot <hi>train up his child in the way he ſhould go,</hi> if he do not know the way himſelf: We read <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>Theſe words ſhall be in thy heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> it's fitly render'd in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, thou ſhalt <hi>whet or ſharpen</hi> them; the word of God is more keen and ſharp when it hath firſt done its work on the parents hearts, and ſo comes from their hearts to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Parents muſt keep their own graces in exerciſe, to put authority and ſavour in all that they ſay and do for the ſalvation of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Grace muſt work in their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98500:39"/>prayers; grace muſt rule their tongues; grace muſt guide the rod, and grace muſt ſhine in their lives: and then it's a great work which is to be wrought in the children; it is a great work for them who are <hi>born of the fleſh,</hi> to be <hi>born of the ſpirit;</hi> a great work to make Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Godlineſs natural to them; to make the <hi>children of the devil</hi> to become the <hi>children of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> and parents muſt conſtantly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the uſe of means to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh this work.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Be mighty in prayer for your children; for all the good ye deſire for them muſt come from God, and therefore muſt be beg'd by prayer; it is in vain for them to be taught of us, except they be taught of God; <hi>Whoſe words, Lord,</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Auguſtine) were they but thine, which by my faithful mother thou haſt ſung in my heart.</hi> Pray, and pray in faith and hope; <hi>thy ears</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98500:39"/>again) <hi>were at my mothers heart, when ſhe pray'd for me;</hi> ye muſt pray with tender and melting hearts: the ſame Father tells us, that his mothers tears watered the earth when ſhe pray'd for him: and ye muſt pray for their ſalvation: this alſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls the <hi>hinge</hi> of his holy mothers prayers for him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Solemnly dedicate them to God by baptiſm; and then ye muſt heartily conſent that God alone be the eternal life and happineſs of you and your children, and that Jeſus Chriſt be their and your Redeemer, to redeem you and them from all ſin and miſery, and to bring both to God; and that the Holy Ghoſt be their and your Sanctifier, that by him you and they may have a Scripture-right unto, and be made meet and fit for this happineſs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When they are capable of it, inſtruct them in the Covenant, which by baptiſm they were ſolemnly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98500:40"/>into. For this end ye muſt diligently teach them theſe ſix things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To know the evil and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſin; for till they come to know what ſin is, and what it is to be ſaved, or damn'd, and what it is to loſe, or enjoy God; they will not value or accept of Chriſt, but will deſpiſe the Redeemer of the World as good for nothing: ye muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labour to make ſin odious, and Chriſt precious to your children, and then they will value Chriſt, and obey you: It was propheſied of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, that he was to <hi>prepare the way of the Lord, and to turn the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the parents:</hi> ſo let it be your care to make way for Chriſt in your childrens hearts; and if ye prevail in that, they will be obedient to you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Inform your ſelves and them in the doctrine of God the Father,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98500:40"/>Son, and Holy Ghoſt: for this is the doctrine whereinto they are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; and by baptiſm they are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly entered into Covenant with theſe ſacred perſons, againſt the fleſh, Satan, and the world: ſhew them the glory and love of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in chuſing, ordaining, fitting, and ſending Jeſus Chriſt, and in commanding him to be a ſacrifice for us; inform them that God the Father is the fountain of life; for <hi>Chriſt lives by the Father:</hi> the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Authority; for Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>all power in heaven and earth</hi> from him: the fountain of all the Chriſtian Religion; for Chriſt firſt heard theſe truths from the Father, and then made them known to us; and the fountain of glory, for the Father <hi>hath exalted Chriſt,</hi> and all glorified Saints are the <hi>bleſſed of the Father.</hi> Labour by theſe and all other means, that God the Father have the greateſt place in your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98500:41"/>hearts. Teach them to know and prize Jeſus Chriſt; without this they cannot be true Chriſtians: ſhew them all the fulneſs and glory of the Godhead in Jeſus Chriſt: Labour to make them ſee his glory as the only begotten Son of God; and all that he as Mediator and Redeemer hath done in the ſtate of his humiliation, and is doing, and will do in the ſtate of his exaltation, for the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of loſt ſinners. Labour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print theſe great Truths upon their hearts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it was the Will and Law of God the Father, that God the Son in our nature ſhould be a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for our ſins: this fully appears <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5, &amp;c. <hi>A body haſt thou prepared,</hi> or fitted <hi>me,</hi> meaning to be a ſacrifice: and, ſaith he, <hi>Lo I come to do thy will, O God:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. <hi>Thy law is in my heart;</hi> meaning that will and law of the Father, which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98500:41"/>bound him to offer and ſacrifice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for our ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Jeſus Chriſt by <hi>his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the death of the croſs,</hi> did perfectly obey and fulfil this law and will of God the Father.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all ſalvation and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is by the Covenant of Grace ſetled upon all, and only thoſe who believe and obey the Goſpel, only for the ſake of this ſacrifice and obedience of Jeſus Chriſt: and therefore, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10. <hi>By the which will we are ſanctified through the offering of the body of Chriſt once for all:</hi> that is, by Chriſts fulfilling the will of his Father, in once ſacrificing himſelf for ſinners, we and all true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are ſanctified, that is, perfectly ſaved.</p>
            <p>Ye muſt alſo acquaint them with the office and work of the Holy Ghoſt, which our Saviour tells us, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. is to guide or lead
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98500:42"/>them into all truth; that is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to believe, and love, and obey the ſaving-truths of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in the Goſpel: for to the end, that they may know and keep their baptiſmal-covenant, they muſt know how all the Three ſacred perſons, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are intereſted in the great work of Salvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Labour to convince your children of the Excellency of the Life of Religion, and obedience to God: commend this to them as the moſt honourable life; for our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tells us, <hi>John</hi> 12.26. <hi>If any man ſerve me, him will my father honour. What ſhall be done to the man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ahaſuerus) whom the king will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour?</hi> But who is able to tell what ſhall be done to the man whom the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt will honour? Let them alſo know, that this is the wiſeſt life; it's <hi>Jobs</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, <hi>Where ſhall wiſdom be found?</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98500:42"/>and, ſaith he, <hi>Job</hi> 28.28. <hi>Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wiſdom; and to depart from evil, is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:</hi> And further, that it is the ſafeſt life, for God is a <hi>ſhield,</hi> and <hi>rock,</hi> and <hi>wall</hi> to all that obey him; and although ſuch things which they have in common with other men are expos'd to danger and loſs, yet their perſons, and their whole por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is always ſafe; and alſo, that this is the moſt gainful life, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Saints gain God, and Chriſt, and Heaven, and loſe nothing; for we cannot loſe by a Saviour, who ſaves us from all evil, and brings us into the poſſeſſion of all good; and though death it ſelf ſtrips us naked of all things under the Sun, yet death is unſpeakable gain to all who live this life: and ye muſt further aſſure them, that this is the moſt pleaſant life, for it is a life of faith, and love, and praiſe, and joy, and a life of victory over ſin; and they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98500:43"/>who live this life, have all things to pleaſe them; they have God to pleaſe them; Chriſt and his Merits to pleaſe them; and a proſpect of a holy and a bleſſed Eternity to pleaſe them: ye would never be the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers of fools, if ye could perſwade your children to be ſo wiſe, as to prize and love a life of obedience to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Commend to your children the glory and amiableneſs of the Houſe and Church of God: this is the body whereinto they are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; take your child with you, and <hi>go walk about Sion, and go round about her, and tell the towers thereof, and mark well her bulwarks, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider her palaces,</hi> as ye are taught, Pſal. 45.9. Preſent to their view King Jeſus, and <hi>at his right hand ſtanding the Queen</hi> (his Church) <hi>in gold of Ophir,</hi> Pſal. 45.9. ſay to them, as the Angel ſaid to <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 21.9. <hi>Come hither, and I will
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98500:43"/>ſhew you the bride, the Lambs wife:</hi> ſhew them that glorious ſight, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. <hi>The woman cloathed with the Sun, and upon her head</hi> (that bright and glorious conſtellation) <hi>a crown of twelve Stars,</hi> that ſo the company of thoſe who live in communion with God and Jeſus Chriſt, may be deſirable, and delightful to them; and that they may forſake evil company, which is often the bane of youth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Teach them to eſteem aright of Gods Ordinances: for by baptiſm they are ſolemnly admitted into that houſe and family which is bleſſed with theſe, as the means of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Labour to beget in them good thoughts of Gods Miniſters; for ye ſhall ever find, that thoſe children will deſpiſe you who make light of them: teach them to pray; ye can never have comfort in your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren till they cry to God, <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> teach them to know, and prize,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98500:44"/>and long for the Lords-Supper, and therein to take Chriſt and all Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in a little bread and wine: teach them to honour and delight in the Lords-day, as the Diamond in the ring of time; thoſe children are always the honour and joy of their godly parents, who make conſcience to keep holy the Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Make them ſenſible that time is ſhort and precious, that an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of glory and miſery is at hand; and that death, and judgment, and heaven or hell are at the door of young children.</p>
            <p>I ſhall further add five Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to godly parents, to prevent this ſad calamity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour to ſave your children from thoſe ſins which provoke God, and will deſtroy them, as well as from thoſe ſins which will alſo bring
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98500:44"/>loſs and reproach upon you: ſome are ſadly affected to ſee their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren given to drunkenneſs, or whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or the like ſins; but are not ſo much concern'd for their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and impenitency, and want of love to God, and for their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs; which ſhews ſuch parents to have too much of the love of the world, and too little love to God and their childrens ſouls; but we muſt take our meaſures of the evil and danger of ſin from the word of God, which tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. that the <hi>covetous,</hi> as well as <hi>drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and whoremongers, ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdom of God:</hi> and this will teach parents not only to mourn over a debauch'd child, but alſo over a covetous, though he be a wealthy child.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve what ſins your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are moſt prone unto, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to fill them with revenge and hatred againſt thoſe ſins: If your
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98500:45"/>child have a foot, or hand gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gren'd, ye will cut off the incurable member, rather than bury your child; ſo ye ſhould do what ye can to pull out the right eye, and to cut off the right hand; and the right foot of ſin in your children, rather than ſuffer their bodies and ſouls to be caſt into Hell: As ye ſhould eſpecially kill thoſe ſins in your ſelves, which your natures are moſt inclin'd unto; ſo ye ſhould do by your children, who are ſo great a part of your ſelves: we are taught, Prov. 20.11. <hi>That even a child is known by his doing, whether his work be pure, or whether it be right:</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may much diſcern by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and ways of their children in their childhood, what they are like to prove in their riper years; and therefore they muſt obſerve them, that they may encourage them in the good, and diſcourage them in the evil, which they then appear to be moſt bent unto.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98500:45"/>
            <p n="3">3. Chuſe to place your children in families of holineſs and prayer; ye will not plant your trees among briars and thorns; much leſs ſhould ye chuſe to place your children to ſerve thoſe who will not ſerve God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Give them due correction: this hath God commanded to kill their ſins, and to ſave their ſouls, Prov. 23.13, 14. <hi>Withhold not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the child; for if thou beateſt him with the rod, he ſhall not dye: thou ſhalt beat him with the rod, and ſhalt deliver his ſoul from hell:</hi> It is better thy child be whipt, than damn'd; and let not thy childs weeping and crying under the rod move thee to withhold due corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. <hi>Chaſten thy ſon, and let not thy ſoul ſpare for his cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> If your childs bone be out of joint, ye will have it ſet, though he cry and bawl under the hand of the Surgeon; and will ſay, It's better
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98500:46"/>he cry now, than be lame ſo long as he lives; ſo it is better your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren cry now under the rod of their father, than that they ſhould weep and wail for ever under the wrath of the infinite God: and therefore that ye may perform this duty, take theſe five Directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do not allow your ſervants to correct your children; for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is an act of authority, and therefore cannot belong to thoſe who are meerly your ſervants; I would not have parents to permit their children to deſpiſe and abuſe their ſervants; but for parents to ſuffer their ſervants to correct their children, is the way to make their children ſtubborn, their ſervants proud, and themſelves contemptible in the eyes of both.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Convince them that it is your duty to correct them for their ſins; and therefore it is adviſeable, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98500:46"/>you make them get thoſe Scriptures without book, which bind you to correct them; alſo ſome of thoſe Scriptures which condemn the ſins which you correct them for, that their conſciences may juſtifie you in doing your duty; and that they may be more afraid of ſin, than the rod; and of provoking God, than offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Correct them betimes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.24. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. <hi>Chaſten thy ſon while there is hope:</hi> Uſe the rod wiſely to them, before they become ſcourges and ſcorpions to you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Labour to be in a good frame when you correct them, that love, and prudence, and meekneſs, and not rage and fury may govern the rod; and do not exerciſe too much ſeverity towards them, that ye may not <hi>provoke them to wrath,</hi> leſt the wrath of the children prove the grief of the parents.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:98500:47"/>
            <p n="5">5. Pray to God for a bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your correcting them, that it may be effectual to drive out that <hi>fooliſhneſs which is bound up in their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Be good examples to your children; let them not ſee you in any ſin, for that may infect them, and make them deſpiſe you; but let them always ſee you ſhining in the Image of God, and that is the way to make them honour, and obey you in the Lord: live ſo, that ye may ſay to them, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> Chap. 4.9. <hi>Thoſe things which ye have both learned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and heard, and ſeen in us, do, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, I proceed to direct thoſe parents who are under this calamity, how to bear it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:98500:47"/>
               <head>8 <hi>Directions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. Abhor it as a great ſin to faint under this affliction; that is, either to be diſabled for thy duty, or to ſink in thy comforts; for it's a ſign that thou didſt place too much of thy happineſs in thy children, if their wickedneſs make thee faint under this calamity. I ſhall only plead with thee, as <hi>Joab</hi> did with <hi>David,</hi> when he made that bitter lamentation for his ſon <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 Sam. 19.6. <hi>Thou haſt declared this day, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt neither princes, nor ſervants:</hi> So I ſay to thee, thou hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareſt that thou regardeſt not God and Chriſt, if thy ſoul faint under the burden of a diſobedient child.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider what I have proved, that this is an affliction which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily befalls Gods deareſt children: ye muſt not think of this, as if ye were the firſt godly parents of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98500:48"/>children; or as if herein <hi>ſome ſtrange thing happened unto you.</hi> I confeſs where a calamity ſeems ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular or extraordinary, it is more apt to overwhelm the afflicted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will be then apt to think that there is ſome extraordinary diſpleaſure in God againſt them; and to ſay with the Church, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger:</hi> But this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is ordinary, and is conſiſtent with the ſaving and diſtinguiſhing grace of God to them; and is <hi>a rod that hath uſually lain on the lot of the righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider that there might have befal'n thee greater miſeries than this.</p>
               <p>I ſhall inſtance in three greater Evils which would have made thee more miſerable.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:98500:48"/>
               <p n="1">1. Thou mighteſt have been a wicked, an ungodly wretch thy ſelf; and for the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> to have curs'd and damn'd thee for ever, would have made thee unſpeakably more miſerable, than to be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>while with a wicked child.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thou mighteſt have had an ungodly yoke-fellow to be <hi>as rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thy bones: Solomon</hi> ſeems to ſpeak of a troubleſome yoke-fellow, as more grievous than a wicked child, Prov. 19.13. <hi>A fooliſh ſon is the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity of his father, and the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a wife are a continual drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping:</hi> This is like the conſtant drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of rain into a houſe, which rots the building, ſpoyls the goods, and ruins both houſe and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: and foraſmuch as thy yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow is nearer, and ought to be dearer to thee than thy child; to be afflicted therein, is a greater ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:98500:49"/>
               <p n="3">3. God might have left all your children to periſh in their ſins: but if ye have but one godly child, your joy in that ſhould much abate your ſorrow for your other wicked children.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, thou haſt greater things to affect thee with grief and ſorrow than thy wicked children: there are whole Empires and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of men, and women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who have as precious ſouls as thine, or thy childrens: theſe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the ſame God, and periſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his wrath; and multitudes that have the Scriptures and Ordinances, deſpiſe the ſame Chriſt, and the ſame Goſpel as thy children do: and why ſhouldſt thou be more concern'd for one, or more of thy wicked children, than for <hi>the whole world that lies in wickedneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Let your ſorrow be guided by Scripture and Reaſon, that ye may not provoke God, and defile your
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98500:49"/>ſouls, and wound your conſciences by ſinful groans and tears. For this end obſerve two Rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Mourn more for their ſins whereby they provoke and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, and defile and deſtroy themſelves, and others, than for any ſhame or loſs in worldly things that befall you hereby; that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the love of God, and your childrens ſouls, and not the love of the World, hath the greateſt influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on your ſorrow; for I fear that there is uſually in good parents too much of carnal ſorrow, and too little of godly ſorrow in their mourning under this great cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let not thy ſorrow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe thy body, and impair thy health: God doth not require us to mourn more for our childrens ſins, than our own; and he never makes it our duty by ſorrow for either, to deſtroy
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98500:50"/>our bodies, which are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt: and the truth is, that godly ſorrow is the health of the ſoul, and never hurts the body; for Grace is always a friend, and never an enemy to nature; and therefore do not deprive thy ſelf of all opportunities to honour God, and ſerve his Church; do not make thy yoke-fellow deſolate, nor thy children Orphans by ſuch ſorrow, that will neither pleaſe God, nor eaſe thy ſelf, nor do any good to thy wicked and miſerable children.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Labour to get your Graces ſtrengthened under this great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for ye have need of more knowledge, and wiſdom, and faith, and hope, and love, and meekneſs, and patience, to inable and fit you to bear this, than moſt other affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and ye muſt ſee and enjoy more of God and Chriſt, to keep up your hearts under this, than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der moſt other troubles; yet by the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98500:50"/>ſtrength of Chriſt ye may be inabled not only to bear, but to glory in this tribulation; and the greater the trouble is, the more good ye may gain by it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Comfort thy ſelf, in that the greateſt and beſt things which thou haſt moſt pray'd for, and truſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and expected, and chiefly loved and deſired, are all ſafe and ſure.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thy God is, and will be bleſſed and glorious for ever, whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of thy child; all his infinite perfections are working for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Chriſt himſelf is Gods, and doth the whole work of a Mediator as his ſervant, and for his glory; all the bleſſed Angels and Saints will for ever honour, and admire, and love, and praiſe him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are for ever thy own, and will to all eternity be glorified in making thee bleſſed and glorious:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98500:51"/>thou haſt a bad child, but a good God; all thy work will be done, thy ſins pardoned and kill'd, thy graces perfected, and body and ſoul glorified: and ſhall an ungodly child make all thy conſolations herein ſmall to thee?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Conſider, this trouble will laſt but a little while. I confeſs I do not know, or can upon ſearch find any thing that can lift up the heart above this trouble, but the knowledge and ſenſe of the infinite love of God in Chriſt to a mans ſelf, and of that holy and glorious eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which this love will ſhortly bring him unto; to tell you, that this is and hath been the caſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly parents, may allay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of your grief: But what is this, but to tell you, that others are, and have been as miſerable as you? or to tell you, that as wicked chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as yours have been ſanctified and ſaved, yields ſome hopes; but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98500:51"/>it can amount to no more than to think they may be ſav'd, or thy may be damn'd; and there is as much reaſon to fear the one, as to hope for the other: But for a man to ſee a gainful death, ready to looſe him into that world, where there is none of this ſorrow; and to know that at the day of judgment his wicked children will be no more to him than bloody <hi>Bonners,</hi> or <hi>Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> or damn'd Devils, and that he himſelf ſhall ſit with Chriſt to judge them; and that he ſhall love and delight in the holineſs and juſtice of the Judg of all the World, in paſſing that ſentence upon them, <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting ſire, prepared for the devil and his angels:</hi> This is ſufficient to overcome all immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate grief for his ungodly children.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I ſhall finiſh this diſcourſe in a ſerious exhortation to theſe ungodly children, who are the grief
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98500:52"/>and bitterneſs of their good parents: And herein I ſhall,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Endeavour to convince them of their ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of their miſery.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Perſwade them to forſake their ſins, that ſo they may be freed from that miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall ſet before you the greatneſs of your ſins in theſe four particulars:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Ye have broken your Covenant with God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ye have broken the Bonds wherein ye were bound to the Church of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ye have broken the Bonds of your duty to your parents.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ye have broken the Bonds of your duty to your other rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98500:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Ye have broken your Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, whereinto ye were ſolemnly enter'd by baptiſm; for it's clear by that Scripture before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.3. That by caſting off the authority of your parents, ye have diſowned the Lord to be your God. Your breach of Covenant with God appears more fully in theſe four particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Ye do in your hearts and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices deny the Being of God; the firſt Article of the Covenant is, that ye ſhould acknowledge and believe that the Lord he is God; for <hi>he that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is,</hi> Hebr. 11.6. But this is the language of your hearts and lives, <hi>That there is no God:</hi> Ye deny God to be the firſt and beſt Being, in preferring the creatures before him; and ſaying in effect, That the creatures are all, and the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> is but as a cypher to you.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:98500:53"/>
               <p>Ye deny his Omnipreſence; he fills all places where ye are, but ye take no notice of him; the preſence of a Father or Maſter hath ſome influence upon you; but it works not at all upon you, that there is a God in the room.</p>
               <p>Ye deny his infinite Wiſdom, that Wiſdom of God in contriving the work of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt: I ſay that Wiſdom which is ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and wonderful to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers of heaven, is to ſuch proud and ignorant boys and girls as you, but a fooliſh and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous thing.</p>
               <p>Ye deny his Power, in daring to war againſt him; and like thoſe hectoring Atheiſts, <hi>Job</hi> 15.25, 26. <hi>Ye ſtretch out your hands againſt God, and ſtrengthen your ſelves againſt the Almighty: ye run upon him, even on his neck, upon the thick boſſes of his buckler,</hi> as if ye were able to fight God, and overcome the Almighty.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:98500:53"/>
               <p>Ye deny his Holineſs, and think that God <hi>is altogether ſuch a one as your ſelves,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. And that ye may not be terrified by your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and unlikeneſs to him, ye will pleaſe your ſelves in fancying that God is like you; as if ye muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a pattern to him, than he be a pattern to you; and ſo ye will perſwade your ſelves that he is the God of Atheiſts, and Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Drunkards, and Lyars, and Thieves, and not the holy God of a holy people.</p>
               <p>Ye deny the Truth of God; one of the greateſt and beſt truths that ever God ſpake to man is that, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11. <hi>God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son:</hi> and yet herein ye would <hi>make him a liar,</hi> in not believing this ſolemn record which he gave of Chriſt; a liar is one of the worſt characters of the devil: and this ye give to the true and holy God. Theſe things I write,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98500:54"/>as it were, upon the brazen faces of all ungodly and diſobedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ye break the Covenant, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to take God for your God and happineſs; the greateſt promiſe that ever God made to man, is that Hebr. 8.10. <hi>I will be to you a God:</hi> but this ſignifies nothing to you, ye will not accept of him for your chief honour, and treaſure, and joy; it is no honour to you to have the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> for your F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther; ye ſee no good in him, and account not your ſelves the better for him; and if ye loſe him, ye think ye loſe nothing; ye neither love, nor deſire him, nor take any delight or pleaſure in him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ye have broken the Covenant, in renouncing God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, in whoſe Name ye were baptized: your lives declare that ye had rather have the love of a debauch'd companion, than the love of the Father of Jeſus Chriſt;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98500:54"/>ye deſpiſe the Lord Jeſus, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the great price of redemption to be worth nothing; and would rather keep your ſins, than be ſaved from them: ye defie the wrath of God, and ſcorn that the Mediator ſhould make your peace with him: ye reſiſt the Holy Spirit, and would rather be made filthy, and wicked, and be taught to lye, and ſwear, and ſteal, than that the Spirit ſhould teach you to love, and ſerve, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ye have broken the Covenant, in taking part with the devil, and the world, and ſin, againſt the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt: and this ye have done two ways:</p>
               <p n="1">1. In believing the promiſes of the devil, the world, and ſin, and in not believing the promiſes of God; the devil, the world, and ſin, are the three great cheats of mankind, and they deceive men by making ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98500:55"/>great and high promiſes: and by theſe they have prevail'd with man to break both the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of Grace: the devil tempted our firſt parents not to believe that word of God which he gave them to deter and keep them from ſin, which word is written, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> the devil tempted them to look on that word as a lye, and makes them that great promiſe, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.4, 5. wherein he promiſeth them, that if they eat the forbidden fruit, they ſhall not only be ſafe from all evil, ſaying, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely dye;</hi> but that they ſhall alſo be preferr'd to greater happineſs than God had then placed them in; for, ſaith he, <hi>your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as gods, knowing good and evil:</hi> and by believing this promiſe of the devil, they brake the Covenant of Life, and brought that deluge of ſin and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98500:55"/>miſery which came upon all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and ſince he prevail'd with men not to believe the word of God, which he ſpake to keep them from ſin and deſtruction; now his work is to tempt them to make God a lyar in the word which he hath ſpoken to ſave them from ſin and ruine by Jeſus Chriſt: and this is the word of the Covenant of Grace, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth eternal life and ſalvation to all that believe in Chriſt, and repent of their ſins, and live the lives of new creatures, according to the rules of the Goſpel: but the devil tempts men to break this Covenant by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them life and all happineſs in a courſe of ſin; and theſe wicked children believe the devil herein, and bleſs themſelves in their ſins, ſaying with thoſe bold <hi>ranters,</hi> Deut. 29.19. <hi>We ſhall have peace, though we walk in the imagination of our own hearts, to add drunkenneſs to thirſt:</hi> and thus ye break your Covenant with God,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98500:56"/>and make a Covenant with Death and Hell.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In obeying the devil, the world, and ſin, and in diſobeying God; ye call God your <hi>Father in heaven,</hi> but ye do the luſts of the Devil your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hell; <hi>ye walk according to the courſe of this world,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2. <hi>and are the ſervants of ſin,</hi> Rom. 6.20. and ye hate, and fight againſt God your Maker and Redeemer; and were it poſſible for you, ye would every day kill him who only hath immortality: And thus like a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>renegado's</hi> ye live as if ye were baptized in the name of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the world, and the fleſh, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Ye have broken the Bonds of your duty to the Church of God; ye were born members of the Church, and ſubjects of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Jeſus Chriſt; and by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm were ſolemnly admitted into that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98500:56"/>great, and holy, and victorious, and bleſſed ſociety, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>Mount Sion, the City of the living God, the heavenly Jeruſalem, the general aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly and Church of the firſt-born written in heaven;</hi> but ye have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken this Church, and turn'd your ſelves out of the family and houſe of the living God, and are become of the ſame party with the devil and his ſeed, and have laboured to fill the world with ſin, and the kingdom of Satan; and ye would have Jeſus Chriſt to have no Name, or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or Miniſters, or Ordinances, or People in the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Ye have broken the Bonds of your duty to your parents: This appears in that thoſe black characters already given of wicked children are found on you; whereunto I ſhall add this one, which includes all the particulars of your diſobedience which can be mention'd, namely,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98500:57"/>Ye do not love your parents; for love worketh no evil unto, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways willeth and ſeeketh the good of the beloved: Love ever inclines perſons to pleaſe them whom they love, and to love and delight in their company; and cauſeth ſuch looks, and words, and behaviour, as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of love; how pleaſant hath it been ſometimes to me to ſee, as it were, the heart and ſoul of a child running out in his pleaſant and loving looks to his parents! but ye diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children do not love your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but do them more hurt, and cauſe them more ſorrow than all the malicious enemies and perſecutors they ever met with in the world; ye are always vexing, and croſſing, and provoking them, and are as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>pricks in their eyes, and thorns in their ſides;</hi> and had rather be with lyars, and ſwearers, and drunkards, and with your wanton and idle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, than with your wiſe, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98500:57"/>grave, and holy parents; how merry and jovial are ye in the company of ſuch who will joyn with you to ſerve the devil, and diſhonour God, and deſtroy your ſouls? but how uneaſie, and lumpiſh, and ſowre, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent are ye in the preſence of your parents? your ſpiteful looks, and ſullen words, and ſcornful carriage doth betray your hatred, and anger, and envy againſt your good parents: Ah wicked wretches! that ye cannot find in your hearts to love your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, from whom ye had your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings under God, and who have us'd all holy means to make you holy and bleſſed.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Ye have broken the Bonds of your duty to your other relations, and to all men; ye cannot be good brothers, or ſiſters, whil'ſt ye are ſuch bloody children to your parents; ye cannot be good ſervants or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, or good husbands or wives, or good ſubjects to Magiſtrates, whilſt
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98500:58"/>ye are bad children; for the ſame ſins that debauch you in that relation, will debauch you in all, and will make you an incumbrance to your place, the troublers of the world, and a very plague and curſe to your ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I ſhall now endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of your miſery; and oh that I had a heart and tongue to think and ſpeak of this as the matter doth require! Conſider, ye are curſed children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.16. <hi>Curſed be he that ſetteth light by his father or his mother, and all the people ſhall ſay, Amen:</hi> Obſerve, God himſelf doth here proclaim you curſed; he only can curſe or bleſs you, having all curſes and bleſſings at command; and can ſet his love, or pour out his wrath where he pleaſeth; he is able and faithful to fulfil his own threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; and he knows you to be curſed, for he knows all the children of his Grace, and all the children of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98500:58"/>his Wrath. Obſerve further, that all Gods Miniſters are to pronounce you curſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>The Levites ſhall ſpeak and ſay to all the men of Iſrael with a loud voice, Curſed be he that ſetteth light by his father or his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> The Miniſters of God muſt with a loud voice, as if they would ring in the years of all, declare you to be curſed; and I, a Miniſter of the Goſpel, do hereby proclaim all wicked and diſobedient children, (though ſome of them may be the fruit of my own body) to be curſed. Nay further, all people, yea your own ſelves are to judge you curſed; <hi>and all the people ſhall ſay, Amen:</hi> They and you are to believe it, and to approve of it as moſt juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, that ye be curſed. But that I may convince you of your miſery, I ſhall further ſet before you theſe four things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Ye are out of the way of all good: God hath his way of mercy,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98500:59"/>and his way of wrath; and ye are out of the way of his mercy, for ye do not ſtand in the grace and love of God, which cauſeth all good; and are children of his wrath, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all miſery; and (as I have told you) ye have broken that Covenant which conveys all Grace and Mercy: ſo that no good can come to you, except ye turn to God and your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ye are in the very way and road to all wickedneſs: Many of the moſt horrid ſins in the world firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in diſobedience to parents; and moſt of thoſe who have proved Lyars, Drunkards, Whoremongers, Thieves, Murderers, were firſt ungodly and diſobedient children.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ye are in continual danger of ſome remarkable judgment of God in this life, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.17. <hi>He that curſeth</hi> (or revileth) <hi>his father, or his mother, ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> Prov. 20.20. <hi>Who ſo curſeth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98500:59"/>or his mother, his lamp ſhall be put out in obſcure darkneſs.</hi> Your lamp of life and pleaſure may ſeem to burn and ſhine at preſent, but there is a black and diſmal night ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening on all diſobedient children, Prov. 30.17. <hi>The eye that mocketh his father, and deſpiſeth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley ſhall pick it out, and the young eagles ſhall eat it:</hi> None are more like to paſs into the eternal world, through a ſhameful and untimely death, than diſobedient children; when God leaves children to diſobey their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, it's a dreadful ſign of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching ruine: it's recorded of <hi>Eli</hi> his ſons, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25. <hi>That they hearkned not unto the voice of their father, becauſe the Lord would ſlay them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If ye go on in your courſe of diſobedience, ye will for ever be damn'd in Hell; for (I ſay) ye have broken that Covenant which promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98500:60"/>eternal life to all that believe and obey the Goſpel, and doth as certainly bind over to the wrath and vengeance of God all that live in diſobedience to God and their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. Miſerable children! I have ſent this poor little book to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you, before the wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God do overtake you: I am not altogether a ſtranger to <hi>the terrors of the Lord,</hi> but do know what is before you, and what a meeting there will quickly be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and you, better than ye do; and have laboured to affect my heart, in ſeeing what lies at your door; I know that whilſt ye are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the chaſe of your filthy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, evil from God is hunting you, and will find you out to deſtroy you; and I dare not damn my own ſoul by not warning you of thoſe ſins, which will be the damnation of yours: Fooliſh boys and girls can now laugh at the hearing of death, and hell, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98500:60"/>judgment to come; and when Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſound the trumpet in their ears, to give them warning of theſe things, they can, like the War-horſe in <hi>Job,</hi> ſay among the trumpets, Aha; for the devil tempts his children to make ſport of thoſe things at which he trembles himſelf: but when I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how I have ſeen in ſome of you your down-looks, your pale-faces, your ſhivering-limbs; and as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of the Adulterer, when he comes to be known, <hi>Job</hi> 24.17. that ye have been as <hi>in the terrors of the ſhadow of death,</hi> when your mortal parents have found you out in your ſins: I cannot but think how your countenances will fall, and your ſtout ſpirits ſink, and your mettal fail, when ye come to <hi>fall into the hands of the living God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, I come now to exhort and perſwade you to abhor and forſake your ſins, that ye may eſcape this
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98500:61"/>miſery. I would have you to repent and believe with the Saints of God, that ye may be ſaved, before ye come to repent with the damned in hell; and with the devils, to <hi>believe and tremble.</hi> For this end I ſhall, 1. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to convince you of your Folly. 2. Direct you how to attain true Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of your Folly: ye ſee the Text calls a wicked ſon, a fooliſh ſon; God who knows you beſt, and hath a true judgment of you, calls you fools, and would have all the world to be of the ſame judgment with himſelf, and therefore to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count you fools; and ye will at laſt call your ſelves fools, when ye come to have the portion of fools; and except ye judge your ſelves fools, ye cannot be wiſe. And that ye may, as in a glaſs, ſee your own folly, I ſhall propound to you theſe five Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and as God ſaid to <hi>Job,</hi> ſo do I
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98500:61"/>in his name ſay to you, <hi>Job</hi> 38.3. <hi>Gird up your loins like men: I will demand of you, and anſwer ye me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Are ye not very fools in that ye do in your hearts and lives deny the being of God? There are no worſe <hi>fools than they that ſay in their hearts, There is no God,</hi> Pſal. 14.1. For ſuch a one ſaith in effect, that there is no Religion, no Sin, no Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven nor Hell; yea, he ſaith, that he himſelf is nothing, and that there are neither Heavens, nor Earth, nor Seas, nor Men, nor Beaſts, nor any other creatures; for if there be no God, there can be nothing elſe; ſo that ye have the name of fools written on your foreheads; and as it's ſaid, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.3. Ye ſay to every man that ye are a company of fools.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are ye not fools to make ſuch a fooliſh choice? It is the infinite goodneſs of God, that ye have life and death, bleſſing and curſing ſet before you; and that ye have a God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98500:62"/>and Chriſt, and the Holy Spirit, and the heavenly glory to chuſe; and ye have Beings capable to chuſe them, and may take them for your own, and uſe them as your own every day, and that ye are called and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to chuſe them, and have time and opportunity to chuſe them, and ſhall certainly have them, if ye chuſe them: and yet theſe, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.16. are but <hi>as a price in the hands of a fool that hath no heart to it.</hi> Conſider, there are two ſorts of Affections in all humane creatures, and all are wiſe or fools, according as they ſet and place theſe; there are affections of union, as love, deſire, and delight, which do unite the heart to their objects; and there are affections of oppoſition, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and anger, which do ſeparate the heart from their objects: And are ye not monſtrous fools, in that ye hate and abhor God and your Redeemer, in whom there are all reaſons for
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98500:62"/>your love, and deſires, and joy; and in that ye love, and deſire, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſin, and the devil, and death and hell, in whom there are all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the hatred and revenge of your ſouls? To love thoſe things which are altogether loathſome, and and to hate what is altogether lovely, is a plain argument of your madneſs and folly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Are ye not fools in ſuffering every thing to deceive you? The Scripture tells you, that the devil is a deceiver; it tells you of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of your hearts; of the deceitfulneſs of ſin; of the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of riches; of the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of wine and ſtrong drink; of the deceitfulneſs of harlots, who promiſe pleaſure, but prove <hi>a deep ditch, and a narrow pit;</hi> of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of a <hi>lying tongue,</hi> which promiſeth that lyes ſhall ſerve the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars turn, and do his work, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to be but <hi>for a moment;</hi> of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98500:63"/>deceitfulneſs of theft and unjuſt gain, which ſeems ſweet at preſent, but ſoon after proves as <hi>gravel in the mouth:</hi> and yet notwithſtanding all the ſhame, and rags, and ſtings, and torments of conſcience, which have come upon you by truſting in theſe; yet ye will ſtill believe them, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your ſelves by theſe deceivers to be cheated of God and Chriſt, and of your ſouls, and of your time, and of heaven.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Are ye not fools in being ſo ſet and bent to ruine and deſtroy your ſelves? <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.7. <hi>A fools mouth is his own deſtruction, and his lips are the ſnare of his ſoul.</hi> Eccleſ. 10.12. <hi>The lips of a fool ſhall ſwallow up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> ye are ſo bent on your own ruine, that your hearts riſe in anger and hatred againſt your good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Miniſters, and all that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſave you; and ye account them your worſt enemies, who would not have you damn'd. Miſerable
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98500:63"/>children! allow your ſelves but one hours ſerious conſideration of your eternal eſtate, and ye will ſee reaſon to condemn your ſelves for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of proud and ignorant fools, in attempting to run down God, and his Kingdom, and Religion, and in valuing your cups, and luſts, and lies at ſuch a rate, as for them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change the eternal life and happineſs of your ſouls.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Are ye not fools in not prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for death and judgment, which are ready to overtake you? To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of this, be inform'd, That men are prepared for death and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who by faith, and repentance, and holineſs, are become heirs of the promiſes of the Goſpel, and ſo have a right unto, and fitneſs for all that glory, which in performance of theſe promiſes, God will give them the poſſeſſion at thoſe great days; but men are unprepared when they are under the wrath and curſe of God,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98500:64"/>and are condemned to thoſe eternal torments which are threatned in the Scriptures, and will at death and judgment be executed upon them. Now prove your ſelves by theſe things, and ye may then ſee what fools ye are, in not preparing for theſe days; for if ye were prepared, ye ſhould then enter into a world where all will love you; God, and and Chriſt, and all Angels, and all Saints will love you, and ye will for ever be holy and bleſſed in their love to you, and in your love to them; but being unprepared, ye muſt then be caſt into a world where all will hate you, and where you will hate all the holy and bleſſed; God will there hate you, and be a conſuming fire againſt you; the devils, and all the damned in hell will hate you, and you will hate them; and we find that our Saviour brands him for a fool, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. who promiſeth to himſelf an eaſie and merry life for
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98500:64"/>many years, when that very night he was to loſe his ſoul: and he gives the character of fooliſh virgins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.2. to thoſe who were unprepared for that great, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and ſudden cry, <hi>The bridegroom is come, go ye out to meet him.</hi> Poor children! let theſe common things be imprinted on your hearts; Death is certain, the day of death is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly appointed, as was the day of your birth; and as your birth kept its time, ſo will your death keep its time; ye cannot ſin away death, though ye ſin away the ſenſe of death. Conſider alſo, that death is near; whatever ye think of your lives, they will be but as a vapour, or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or ſmoke, as God ſpeaks them to be; and though ye put death far from you, yet it will be within a hands-breadth of you; one day or hour may put an end to your ſpace of repentance, and conclude your day of grace and ſalvation, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98500:65"/>you into that world where no new creatures are made: ye now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie death, as if ye were a fit match for the king of terrors; ye ſcorn the grave, and ſcoff at the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deride everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but when God ſhall <hi>pour upon you your own wickedneſs,</hi> Jer. 14.16. then ye will too late condemn your ſelves for fools, when ye come to reap the fruit of your own folly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I come to give you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to direct you to true Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that ye may be ſuch <hi>wiſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as to make glad fathers,</hi> and not to be <hi>the heavineſs of your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Do not dare to put off your repentance any longer; it is not too late to repent, ſo long as God calls you to repentance, and gives you time for it: <hi>Yet is the accepted time, yet is the day of ſalvation:</hi> God, and Chriſt, and Angels, and the Church,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98500:65"/>and your bleeding parents are yet ready to receive you in love and joy: but it will ſhortly be too late to repent, though it can never be too ſoon. Dear children! ye muſt either perſwade your ſelves that the word of God is a lie, and ſo think ye are ſecure from hell, becauſe ye deny the Bible that threatneth it; or ye muſt preſume that ye are not ungodly children, as indeed ye are; or elſe ye muſt conclude that your preſent ſtate is not ſafe and good, and that therefore ye muſt either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent or be damn'd; and perhaps the devil himſelf doth not tempt you to reſolve, that you will never repent, but to think that it is yet time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and that therefore ye will repent hereafter. I have ſometimes dreaded to hear debauch'd children confidently ſay, That they do not queſtion but they ſhall be converted, and become good, when at preſent they hate to be reformed; yea, I am
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98500:66"/>perſwaded that ſome ſecure them ſelves in their ſins, by preſuming that the prayers of their good parents for their converſion and ſalvation will at laſt be heard: but how many ſuch have been, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32.—<hi>driven away in their wickedneſs;</hi> in whom that dreadful Scripture hath been fulfill'd, Prov. 29.1. <hi>He that being often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, hardneth his neck, ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</hi> I ſhall here ſeriouſly reaſon this caſe a little with you; Why ſhould ye continue one moment longer in thoſe ſins which ye muſt repent of, or periſh; and defer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, for which ye ſhall have cauſe for ever to rejoyce and bleſs God when it is done? Are ye not wicked enough already, that ye muſt ſtay to be worſe? Have ye not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd your ſelves, and provok'd God, and refus'd Chriſt, and afflicted your parents long enough already? Poor
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98500:66"/>ſouls! if there be one hour yet left wherein ye are ſure that ye ſhall not die, and fall into hell; or one hour wherein ſin is better than grace; and wherein it is better be a child of the devil, than a child of God; or if ye can come into the kingdom of God, and begin an eternal life an hour too ſoon, take that hour, and ſpend it on your luſts; but if not, ſtop pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and let this be the hour wherein ye begin to believe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and reform, and wherein ye begin to ſet your faces towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with an unmovable reſolution, to walk in the way of faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience till ye come there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Direct.</hi> 2. Judge whether ye have more reaſon to obey the devil, or to obey God, as the Apoſtles ſaid to their Perſecutors, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19. <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken to you more than unto God, judge ye:</hi> So ſay I to you, whether
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98500:67"/>it be right to obey the devil rather than God, judge ye. Conſider, God hath authority to command you, for he is your Maker, your Preſerver, and Redeemer, and ye owe your ſelves to him; but the devil neither made, nor kept, nor bought you, and therefore can have no right to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you. Conſider further, that all the Commands of God, are the Commands of his Love; for he doth not only command you as your Lord, but alſo as your Father and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and therefore he commands you to take himſelf to be your God and happineſs, to take his Son Jeſus Chriſt to ſave you from all evil, and to make you for ever holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but the devil commands you out of hatred and malice, and all his commands are the commands of a Murderer, and therefore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you to defile, and to deſtroy, and to damn your ſelves; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you to be blind and ignorant.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98500:67"/>to hate and ſcorn God and Chriſt, and to love ſin, and death, and hell. Conſider alſo, that God is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your obedience, and to puniſh your diſobedience; he is that <hi>only law-giver, who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy,</hi> James 4.12. He can crown you with eternal glory, if ye obey him; and can caſt you into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting flames, if ye diſobey him; but the devil, who is curſed and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented himſelf, cannot make you happy, if ye obey him; nor miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if ye do forſake and renounce him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See the great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe wiſe and holy children, who live in obedience to God and their parents, and you who live in diſobedience to both; it is not wealth, or poverty, or beauty, or deformity, or ſickneſs, or health, but ſin and grace that make the greateſt differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt perſons; and ye muſt know God and Chriſt, or elſe ye
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98500:68"/>cannot underſtand the worth of a Saint, nor the vileneſs of a Sinner: Some of you may look into your own families, and there ſee ſome of your brethren and ſiſters like plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and fruitful plants about your fathers table, when ye are as briars, and thorns, and weeds in the family; they are the crown and joy, and you the calamity of your parents; all that ſee them, may look upon them as a ſeed whom the Lord hath bleſſed; but all that ſee you have reaſon to judge you to be a curſed generation. Poor children! is it better to be like <hi>Cain,</hi> than like <hi>Abel?</hi> or like curſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> than like <hi>Shem?</hi> or like <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> than like <hi>Iſaac?</hi> or like <hi>Eſau,</hi> than like <hi>Jacob?</hi> Are not your ſouls and bodies as precious as the ſouls and bodies of your good brethren and ſiſters? or can the devil, and ſin, and the world be better to you, than to them? or is not death and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as near you, as it is to them?
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98500:68"/>or have not ye as much reaſon to love and obey God and your parents, as they? or can ye endure the loſs of Heaven, or torments of Hell, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they? if not, why ſhould not ye be as good as they are?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Do nothing but what ye are willing ſhould be known; if ye would not have your Parents, and Maſters, and the Magiſtrates, and your Friends and Foes know your lies, and luſts, and theft, and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lords-day, and your haunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil company, do not practiſe theſe things; ye need not fear who knows how holy, and juſt, and ſober, and chaſt ye are: Religion can bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew its ſhining face to God and man; but ſin makes you ſneak, and cowardly, and baſe, and fearful; and imprints marks of diſhonour and ſhame upon your looks and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and fills you with horrour and conſternation, when ye are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. Conſider ſeriouſly, that all
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98500:69"/>from whom your greateſt ſhame and miſery will come, do know you; the devils know you, and will accuſe, and diſgrace, and torment you for the ſame ſins they tempted you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and they will not help you to hide your ſins when time of grace, and repentance, and pardon is paſt; your own hearts and conſciences know you, and will awake out of their preſent ſleep to condemn and ſting you; and God who is greater than all, knows you, and all your ſecret ſins are in the light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and he will bring them all to judgment: and it will then fully appear to Angels, and Devils, and to Saints and Sinners, what ye are.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Therefore be not ſuch now, as ye dare not at the hour of death profeſs your ſelves to be: Religion and Godlineſs is at all times to be profeſs'd before God, and Angels, and Men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>For with the heart man believeth, and with the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98500:69"/>mouth confeſſion is made to ſalvation.</hi> But what monſters would ye appear to your ſelves, if ye did profeſs your ſelves to be what ye are? Suppoſe ye were reading this but one hour before ye dye, and muſt ſay, We are now falling into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; and by that time that the glaſs is run out, and the clock ſtrikes next, we are to give account of our ſelves to the Judg of all the World: Dare ye then ſay, We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves to be haters of God, and children of the devil, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of our holy parents, and that we chuſe the way to hell?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Conſider what account ye can give in being ſuch burdens of the earth, and in being ſo grievous and chargeable to all who are concerned with you: Is it nothing to you to be as biles or ſcabs in the body, or as ſmoke, or a ſtinking ſmell, or an infectious diſeaſe in the houſe and family where ye are, or as weeds in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98500:70"/>garden, to cumber and annoy your place? Ye will pay dear one day for all the ſighs, and groans, and tears which ye have cauſed to your affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted parents and friends; it will ſting you to think that ſo many have been loſers by you, and that your parents, and brethren, and ſiſters, have been ſo much waſted and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed by your coſtly luſts; and that ye have given cauſe to all your wicked companions, to curſe the day that ever they knew you; and that ye have fill'd ſo many other parents beſides your own with grief and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, by infecting, and defiling, and debauching their children: and methinks I hear all theſe ſaying to you, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid to <hi>Achan,</hi> Joſh. 7.25. Ye <hi>have troubled us,</hi> but <hi>the Lord ſhall trouble you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, I ſhall ask you this one queſtion, What would ye have your parents to do with you? their love
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98500:70"/>makes them to be continually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for you; but they know not what to do with you, for all the means which they have yet uſed for your good, hath but aggravated your guilt, and their grief; whilſt they kept you at home, ye did break all the good orders and rules of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the family; at ſet-times for meat and family-worſhip, either your places were empty, or fill'd with ſin; ye diſquieted your parents, waſted the eſtate, defiled, or diſturbed your brethren and ſiſters, and troubled the houſe night and day: When they ſent you to School, ye plaid the truants, grieved and diſhonoured your Maſters, debauch'd your School-fellows, and were a reproach and ſcandal to the School: If they ſet you to be Apprentices, ye hated and wrong'd your Maſters, and were a plague to the family: If any of you were ſent to the Univerſity, ye were the rake-hells of the Colledge, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98500:71"/>the Society was ſick of you, till it had expell'd and caſt you out; if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all other means were us'd, your parents ſent you to Sea, the Atheiſm and Wickedneſs of ſome of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, did you more hurt, than all the Wonders of God in the deep waters did you good; ſo that ye return'd, as if the Sea had made you like it ſelf, more raging and boiſterous than before; inſomuch, that your miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parents can do nothing but ſpend their days in mourning for your ſins, and in praying for your ſalvation, and in labouring to bear patiently your ruine, and to be content to live and die the fathers and mothers of fools.</p>
               <p>And now, Children, I will take my leave of you, and ſhall leave you to the God with whom ye have to do, and with whom ye muſt have to do for ever; he is the God who will plead the cauſe of his own Name,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98500:71"/>and Honour, and of Religion, with you, and who will plead the cauſe of your diſtreſſed parents with you; a God whoſe wrath ye can neither eſcape, nor bear; there is a war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this God and you; and if ye can make it appear that ye are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and wiſer, and ſtronger, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he, ye may go on: But my deſign in all this diſcourſe, is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to believe, and repent, and obey the Goſpel and ſo to make peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt; and for your encouragement, I do aſſure you, that the grace of God, and the Merits of Chriſt are as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſave you from all your horrid abominations, as if ye were as innocent, as when ye were new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born: God, and Chriſt, and Angels, and your Parents, and Friends, and all Saints are ready to rejoyce in your converſion and ſalvation, and your iniquities ſhall never be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned againſt you; but upon your
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98500:72"/>unfeigned turning to him, God will (as he is repreſented in the Parable of the Prodigal ſon) meet you in mercy, and fall on your necks and kiſs you, and entertain you with all the bleſſings of the Goſpel, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Theſe my children were dead, and are alive; they were loſt, and are found.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98500:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
